<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to the answer of Anonymus to Doctor Gauden's Analysis of the sense of the covenant: and under that, to a later tract of one Mr Zach. Crofton of the same fraternity with him. By John Rowland Oxoniensis, CCC. Rector of Footscray in Kent.</title>
            <author>Rowland, John, 1606-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2070</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1038_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207862</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866889</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866889</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92025)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 154:E1038[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to the answer of Anonymus to Doctor Gauden's Analysis of the sense of the covenant: and under that, to a later tract of one Mr Zach. Crofton of the same fraternity with him. By John Rowland Oxoniensis, CCC. Rector of Footscray in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Rowland, John, 1606-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for T.J. and are to be sold at Westminster-Hall, and the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Gauden, John. Analysis.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gauden, John, 1605-1662. --  Analysis.</term>
               <term>Crofton, Zachary, 1606-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Covenants (Church polity) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119177:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> REPLY TO THE ANSWER of <hi>ANONYM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> TO Doctor <hi>Gauden</hi>'s ANALYSIS of the <hi>Senſe of the Covenant:</hi> And under that, to a later TRACT OF ONE M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Zach. Crofton Of the ſame Fraternity with him.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Rowland</hi> Oxonienſis, CCC. Rector of <hi>Footscray</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ficta in natura ſuam redeunt.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>T. J.</hi> and are to be ſold at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall, and the Royal Exchange. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119177:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119177:2"/>
            <head>A REPLY to <hi>Anonymus</hi> his AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SWER to D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Gaudens</hi> Analyſis, <hi>Of the Senſe of the Covenant.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Met by accident with a Pamphlet againſt Doctor <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den's</hi> Analyſis <hi>of the true ſenſe of the Covenant,</hi> and I know there are enough abler than my ſelf to reply to it, if the Learned Doctor wanted any help here, as he doth not, and I am unwilling the Truth ſhould ſuffer any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice by my defects; yet I think my ſelf ſomething concerned in it as a Clergy-man, and Lover of the Truth; wherefore cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving leave of the Reverend Doctor, and the candid interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Reader, I begin with the Title, which runs thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Anatomy of Doctor</hi> Gauden's <hi>idolized Non-ſenſe and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy in his pretended Analyſis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of that ſacred Covenant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I have examined the Doctors words, as I finde them upon this mans credit, as he lays them down (for I have no other Bookes before me than his I undertook to Anſwer) and I can finde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Doctors but ſolid Reaſon, good Authority, and ſound Divinity, neither Non-ſenſe nor Blaſphemy, unleſs he will falſly charge that upon the Doctor, which may more truly be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to himſelf; idolizing a Covenant (which many wiſe and godly men call a <hi>curſed Covenant,</hi> and the word will beat it) with a ſacred Epithite. The Libeller muſt paſs for <hi>Anonymus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath not vouchſafed to ſubſcribe his Name. I wiſh he were aſhamed of his Cauſe: but I think rather it is the old Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian trick, to make men believe he is afraid of perſecution. But mark his words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reader muſt know that the late Long-Parliament, (I mean both the Honorable Houſes) drew up, took and Ordered others to take two ſeveral Covenants in one year.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119177:3"/>
            <p>A fruitful Year of Covenants! when you name the Long-Parliament, you do well to ſay you mean <hi>the two Honorable Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> for all the world knows the two Honorable Houſes will not own all things done by a prevailing Faction in the late long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. How many of the two Houſes took both thoſe Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, I cannot tell; I am perſwaded a great part of them never took them both, but to free themſelves, left their places in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; and of thoſe that did take them, hundreds its likely have repented for it ſince, and were it to be done again, they would never take them, becauſe ſomething contained in them was unlawful; and beſides that, they wanted the Kings confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two ſeveral Covenants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not opportunity to compare them together how ſeveral or differing they were, it may be they were contrary, or rather contradictory one to the other; for ſuch Contrivers ſeldom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long in the ſame mind, knowing not well what they would have. <hi>Two in one year,</hi> the firſt <hi>June</hi> 1643. the ſecond <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 11 the ſame year. Count the moneths, and it is not much above a quarter of a year: they grew apace, and things that are good, ſeldom grow ſo faſt, which made men ſhrewdly to ſuſpect the goodneſs of them. Now you muſt take notice, that it is only the laſt (the far better of the two) which this Maſter of words hath oppoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His idle Jeſts againſt the learned Doctor are not worth taking notice of, and therefore I let them paſs: But for his Covenants, I believe the firſt was not very good, being like the point of the weapon that makes the entrance, or the ſting of a ſerpent by which the poiſon is firſt conveyed; yet if there were any barrel better herring, I think that was the beſt, becauſe it was the firſt; for miſchief ſtill increaſeth from bad to worſe, <hi>&amp; nemo repente fit turpiſſimus.</hi> The firſt Covenant was preſſed upon the people with as much violence as might be, that who ever would not take it, ſhould bear no Office in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal, by reaſon of the ſecond tayl that was to follow it: Or rather the two Covenants may be compared to the Serpent <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phisbaenae</hi> with two heads. What was the meaning of that, they can beſt interpret that gave it forth, by menacing thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119177:3"/>it. For when King <hi>Charls</hi> the I deſired the Earl of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords</hi> life to be ſpared, and he ſhould bear no Office in Church nor State, they replyed, He that was not fit for ſome Office, was not fit to live: and for this, and ſome other reaſons, I thank God I had the grace to refuſe them all.</p>
            <p>Next he quibbles about the Doctors calling his Analyſis, <hi>The looſing of St.</hi> Peters <hi>bonds.</hi> Becauſe he doth not finde St. <hi>Peters</hi> name in the Text quoted, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. but <hi>Acts</hi> the 12. A moſt ridiculous Cavil, as if a man might not lawfully quote two places of Scripture to the ſame purpoſe, the one to fortifie and expound the other, but it muſt be preſently Non-ſenſe and Blaſphemy, as this Libeller will have it to be: he keeps a fearful clutter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, becauſe he cannot finde out the reaſon of this Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>The looſing of St.</hi> Peters <hi>bonds:</hi> but to put him out of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to ſerve him with my beſt conjecture. The learned Doctor hath qualified the harſhneſs of the Covenant, by giving to it the ſofteſt and moſt ſober ſenſe that it is capable of, and it is poſſible that the Doctor himſelf, through humane frailty, in that ſober ſenſe he expoundeth it, took it ſo; but finding it for all this ſmoothing of it over, to be too hard of digeſtion, he doth in my judgement very well to follow the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of our bleſſed Saviour to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> Luke 22.23, <hi>And thou being converted, ſtrengthen thy brethren;</hi> and therefore he calls his Analyſis, <hi>The looſing of St.</hi> Peters <hi>bonds.</hi> He is very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry becauſe the Doctor will not be one of the rigid Presbyters, that will hold communion with none but ſuch as are of their own opinion; and therefore accuſeth him falſly for <hi>upholding commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Popery,</hi> by reaſon of theſe words he alledgeth, that the Doctor ſaith, <hi>He deſireth to hold not onely all inward, but all actual communion in all Doctrines and Duties of Faith and Worſhip to the Word of God, with the Church of</hi> Rome. If this be not well ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, I wonder what one can ſay to pleaſe him! He had little cauſe to fear the Doctor would turn Roman Catholick, who was ſo much offended with ſome enormities he had formerly taken notice of in Epiſcopal Government; and being as it appears by his Analyſis, a charitable man, and of a tender conſcience, was willing to comply with all Chriſtians in Worſhip <hi>agreeable to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119177:4"/>Word of God;</hi> And this <hi>Anonymus</hi> deſerves for his uncharitable cenſure, and ſo frequently ſcoffing at the Doctors ſighs and tears, to be ſeverely cenſured himſelf, who loves to maintain diviſions in the Church of God, and will not, as it ſeems by him, hold communion with any but ſuch as are of their Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſe bonds were then looſed? The bonds of Goal-birds, thieves, and perhaps murtherers, and other rogues and malefactors, for they are the uſual gueſts in ſuch places, if any ſuch have taken the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I know none that were more fit to take it than ſuch, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs not a few of them did take it, to bolſter them up in their villany; they found favor, when others that had not taken it, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for ſmaller matters. But who doth he call <hi>Goal-birds?</hi> &amp;c. He cannot be ignorant that in the times that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were caſt in priſon, nay our bleſſed Savior himſelf, that thieves and murtherers were often let go free, the beſt Chriſtians were the ordinary Goal-birds: And was it not ſo, when your Covenant was in force? were not the beſt of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry, the graveſt and moſt pious Fathers of the Church, and the moſt learned and Orthodox Divines plundred, ſequeſtred, and caſt into priſon by your Covenanters? deny it if you can. 'Tis true, when Godly Kings ruled over us, the caſe was far otherwiſe; and we doubt not when the Land is once well rid of your Covenant, but that thoſe who do well, ſhall live peaceably under His Sacred Majeſty that now is, (whom God proſper and preſerve) and that none but ſuch as ought to be put into priſons, and ſuch as are oriminal, ſhall be the common gueſts in ſuch places, as they were formerly.</p>
            <p>He promiſeth to <hi>uſe all brevity in his Reply,</hi> and for my part I ſhall do ſo too, being not willing to beſtow much time, or to ſpend ink and paper upon ſuch a Scribler as he is.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>I. Propoſition.</head>
               <p>The Doctor himſelf doth admit the Covenant to be in ſome ſenſe lawful and good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Here is evidence enough againſt the Doctor, that the Covenant is lawful and good, or how elſe could he give a ſober ſenſe of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119177:4"/>
               <p>Men that are ready to ſink, will lay hold of any thing to ſave themſelves: You may ſee an example of it, 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.33. Now the man did diligently obſerve whether any thing would come from him, and did haſtily catch at it: And they ſaid, <hi>Thy Brother Benhadad:</hi> This is meer ſophiſtry to conclude <hi>à dicto ſecundum quid ad dictum ſimpliciter.</hi> The Doctor doth admit the Covenant in ſome ſenſe to be lawful and good; it ſeems it hath many ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and I think ſo too, that it was an equivocal Compact; but in what it may be admitted to be lawful and good, I conſeſs I could never yet underſtand, for the beſt you can make of it, 'tis no better but an invention of factious Noveliſts, contrary to the rule of all Antiquity, to ſubvert and caſt down an ancient, primitive Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Government by Biſhops, and to ſet up a new fangled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart Presbytery in the room thereof, which hath ſtrangely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched ignorant and illiterate men taken with novelties: and I have heard how that <hi>Philip</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> fell in love with it, yet being asked what <hi>Claſſical</hi> was? He ſaid, <hi>Presbyterial:</hi> and what was <hi>Presbyterial</hi> but <hi>Synodical?</hi> a man doubtleſs of a ſtrong faith to believe as the Church believes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He quotes the Doctors words, <hi>That he believes few took it in any ſenſe againſt primitive, reformed, regular Epiſcopacy, &amp;c.</hi> as the reverend Primate of <hi>Armagh</hi> propoſed in his Reduction of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, and hence he infers, <hi>If this Reduction be neceſſary, the Government cannot be unlawful, but good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>England</hi> God be praiſed, hath yet ſtore of able Divines to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Epiſcopacy, as it was firſt regulated by the Apoſtles, by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, Fathers, Councels, and Reaſon, againſt all the Adverſaries of it; who pretending ſome Errors in it, and inveighing againſt perſonal faults of ſome Biſhops, would fain extirpate the frame of primitive Eccleſiaſtical Government, as it was here eſtabliſhed by <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Qu. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charls,</hi> of bleſſed memories, and they that do it, we have reaſon to believe would do it, to accompliſh ſome ſiniſter end of their own, to revenge private injuries they ſuppoſe they underwent, or for ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations which it may be they deſerved not, which they think they loſt by the Biſliops: for it can be nothing elſe but malice in the more learned Presbyters, and deluſion in thoſe that are of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119177:5"/>weaker judgements, to oppoſe a received Truth for ſixteen hundred years and upward, in continuance whereof the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been ſo happy, to the amazement and envy of all other National Churches, under the moſt pious Kings and Queens this Land ever bred; and they that labour to diſſolve this form, muſt condemn all our beſt Princes of ignorance and ſuperſtition, and our greateſt and learnedſt Biſhops and Miniſters (whom the world admired for learning and piety) of all the faults they would fain charge this Government with, and muſt extol their own Wiſdom and Zeal before theirs, under a notion of new Lights and further Revelation. I have not ſeen the Reverend Primate of <hi>Armaghs</hi> Reduction, yet I have reaſon to believe that the learned Primate did not attempt to diveſt himſelf of his honors and preferments in the Church (you did that for him, and for the reſt of the Biſhops and eminent Divines) but held it fit that Biſhops ſhould keep a nearer conjunction with Presbytery, than they have done of late years; and in that reſpect I know none of the Clergy that are againſt it, but hold it very fit, and neceſſary that it ſhould be ſo obſerved.</p>
               <p>The Doctor had reckoned up ſome evils, defects, and dangers incident to Epiſcopacy; as Pride, Ambition, &amp;c. <hi>Is not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all this enough, to prove from his own pen, that ſuch a Covenant pre-extirpating ſuch Epiſcopacy, is lawful and good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The learned Doctor <hi>Gauden,</hi> unwilling to break the bonds of peace and unity, if it were poſſible to keep them, explained their Covenant in the calmeſt ſenſe, to the ſupporting of moderate E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy: But this <hi>Anonymus</hi> will not away with any qualiſica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it muſt ſound of nothing but extirpation of Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and to ſpeak plainly, I dare ſay that was the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of it, and the Doctor is miſtaken, to think it will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any ſober conſtruction; for it was doubtleſs another <hi>Trojan</hi> horſe, deviſed by the Politick <hi>Sinons</hi> of the latter Age, full of armed men, and when the walls of Epiſcopacy were broken down, to let it in, it had doubtleſs proved, if God had not been more merciful to us, the utter ruine of Monarchy and Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and overthrown at once both King, Church, and State; for though there were many neceſſary and pious things couched
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119177:5"/>in it, yet I know not any one of them that they have kept ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but the rooting out of Epiſcopacy; nay, they rather chuſe to break all the reſt, that they might fully reak their ſpleen to abol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh that.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>II. Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herein all ſober Chriſtians who underſtand themſelves, agree with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He after his ſcurrilous manner falls upon a diſcreet Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman Sir <hi>L. B.</hi> (as appears by that prudent ſaying of his to the Doctor) <hi>That many ſober and honeſt men are by their once taking the Covenant, ſo ſcared from all complyings with any Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment under any name of Biſhops, or notion of Epiſcopacy, never ſo reformed and regulated, that they fear by looking back to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive, catholick, and univerſal Government of this and all other ancient Churches, to be turned into pillars of Apoſtacy, as</hi> Lots <hi>wife was into a pillar of ſalt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And can you deny this to be true? Many honeſt men who had been ſworn to the King, could at firſt hardly be charmed by you to accept of your enchanted Covenant, and they ſtrained as much to ſwallow it down, as I have ſeen ſome do at a Pill, who never took any before. Was it not ſo with many tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienc'd men, you had much ado to bring them to it, but you dealt with them as Farriers do with their horſes, to put it down their throats with a horn, but when they had been caught by you, as if they had ſworn by the <hi>Stygian</hi>-lake, or drank of the <hi>Lethean</hi> Cup, they forgat all Allegiance to the King, and fell down faſt bound hand and foot with the fetters of your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: nay, you ſtill go on to perſwade them, as you ſeem to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your ſelf, that it is <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> to depart from it, and that there is no remiſſion for thoſe that ſhall break it, but they muſt periſh everlaſtingly; yet there were multitudes that caſt off the Covenant as a thing of no value, after they had been accuſtomed by you to ſeveral Covenants, New Engagements, Negative Oathes, and what not? and could eaſily take as many of them as you will, without any remorſe of conſcience at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He enlargeth his ſecond point againſt the Doctor, <hi>who ſaid that the admitting of ſome Church Government under the name of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119177:6"/>Biſhops reformed and regulated, according to the primitive, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and Apoſtolick Inſtitution,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is not againſt, but very conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>with the Solemn League and Covenant, and the true inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>allowable by God, and all good men that rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand themſelves, who thus far concur with the Doctor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he oppoſeth the ſecond Article of the Covenant, which he ſaith runs thus: <hi>You ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly (through the grace of God) endeavor the extirpation of Popery and Prelacy, that is, Church-Government by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellers and Commiſſaries, their Deans, Deans and Chapters, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, and other depending on that Hierarchy; ſuperſtition, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, ſchiſm, profaneneſs, and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>this expreſly relates to the Prelacy or Epiſcopacy then in being, or in uſe in</hi> England, <hi>which was far from apoſtolick and primitive,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as the Dr. hath confeſſed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if there be any other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy truly apoſtolick and primitive, free from all theſe evils, and agreeable to ſound doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it is far from the ſenſe of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to extirpate it, that it plainly includes a binding of all Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to promote it.</hi> The Epiſcopacy you would promote, is Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery: is that truly Apoſtolick, and free from all thoſe evils? may not a Presbyter lord it as much in his Pariſh, as a Biſhop in his Dioceſs? may not as much pride be coucht under a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Cloak, as under a Biſhops Rocket? examine your ſelves.</p>
               <p>The Doctor, and all others that would bring theſe men to their right underſtanding, do but labor in vain, and may as well waſh the Blackmoor white. I alwayes thought they ſtood more in need of Hellebore to purge their brains, than of reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them. Where the Bee gathers honey, they Spider-like ſuck venome: they are incorrigble, and it is not convenient for ſober honeſt-minded men to go about to convert them; every man may do well to ſpare his pains to undertake to perſwade them to come home to their due obedience. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid right, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 27.22. <hi>Though thou ſhouldeſt bray a fool in a morter among wheat with a peſtel, yet will not his fooliſhneſs depart from him.</hi> But as the Romans gave them over with a <hi>conclamatum eſt,</hi> who did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive in ſeven days, we may rather deſpair of theſe mens return, who have had almoſt thrice ſeven years to underſtand themſelves
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119177:6"/>better, and yet continue their former obſtinacy; and become more obdurate and hardned in their opinions by any yieldings or conceſſions that are made to them by the Epiſcopal party. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> whom moſt knew to be a Proteſtant in his heart, (and I wiſh the Presbyters were but ſo well opiniona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Epiſcopacy, as he was of the Reformed Churches) called an Aſſembly of Proteſtants and Papiſts, to ſee if he could make ſome reconcilement between them. He propounded a queſtion to the Proteſtants, <hi>whether a Papiſt might be ſaved?</hi> They in their judgement of charity ſaid, <hi>that he might.</hi> Then he demanded of the Papiſts, <hi>whether a Proteſtant might be ſaved?</hi> They in their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid and uncharitable opinion replyed, <hi>A Papiſt might but a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant might not.</hi> His determination was, <hi>Let me have no more Religions within my Dominions than that wherein all Chriſtians may be ſaved.</hi> The Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits went away triumphing, as if they had got the day; and ſo do the Presbyters, by reaſon of the Doctors ſober ſenſe of the Covenant, as if they had wan the Goal, whereas all diſcreet men muſt confeſs it is more his Chriſtian charity, than their deſert.</p>
               <p>He repeats what the Doctor ſaid of Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> and others, (who had a great hand in pennning and promoting the Covenant, (and they own'd it to ſome foreign Divines, that the Covenant was levelled at the <hi>(deſpoticum Tyranicum Regimen)</hi> miſ-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not the Government by Epiſcopacy: I am of opinion that Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> that penned and promoted the Covenant, Badger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like kept one hole open for himſelf to paſs forth at; this expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of it was but a reſerve for him; and its probable he would never have ſaid ſo much againſt Biſhops, if he might have been one, or rather the chief amongſt them: But how moderate and meek a Biſhop he would have been, and free from tyranny over his brethren, let thoſe that have ſeen his proceedings all theſe turbulent times, judge.</p>
               <p>In the next place, he undertakes to diſprove what Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> ſaith in theſe words, That it was the ſenſe of thoſe, who with himſelf, had as much right to ſit among them (that is, in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly) I know not whether this gloſs be true or not, as any others; but were not permitted either by popular Faction or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119177:7"/>or by other ſhufflings and reaſons of State, who took care to exclude all the excellent Biſhops of the Church, and the moſt able Epiſcopal Divines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that can have a face of braſs to deny this, and to call it <hi>a very great ſlander,</hi> which almoſt every man can juſtifie, ſhould be confuted as he that denies a God, or ſnow to be white. <hi>Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to baculino non Ariſtotelico.</hi> It would be too tedious for me to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe the whole matter from the beginning, I ſhall therefore give you but one example for all, the proceedings being all alike. I pray what was the reaſon that the reverend Prelare <hi>John Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> with as many Biſhops as durſt joyn with him, at leaſt twelve in number, drew up a Solemn Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Violence that was offered to thoſe eminent Clergy-men that were called by His Majeſties Writ to ſerve in the Upper-Houſe, who durſt not come thither for fear of being murthered by popular tumults raiſed againſt them?</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>The Doctor was not choſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What right Doctor <hi>Gauden</hi> had to ſit there by Election, I am not able to ſay, but this I may ſay, that he and ſuch well-affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons to the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> had more right to ſit there than many that did, who ſate onely to ſtir up Contentions in Church and State, to uphold Factions, and overthrow the beſt Governments formerly ſetled by the Laws of the Land, ſuch as no other part of the world is able to parallel: had he not reaſon then (taking the Denomination ſynechdochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, from the greater and not the better part, who were but few in number in reſpect of the other) to call it <hi>a Sequatious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, A grand Inqueſt,</hi> &amp;c. as you ſay. And had he not cauſe enough to deſire to ſit there, that he might by his judicious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, help thoſe that were too few to ſtop the fury of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians againſt the Biſhops?</p>
               <p>He quarrels with him, <hi>about being Parſon of the Deanery of Bocking</hi> in <hi>Eſſex, worth</hi> 4, <hi>or</hi> 500 pound <hi>per Annùm, who to his ſhame, and little honor to thoſe employed him, is non reſident from it, and preacheth at the</hi> Temple.</p>
               <p>If his Parſonage had been better worth (though I can hardly believe you that it is worth ſo much) it is like he well deſerved
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119177:7"/>it, for thoſe who preach at the <hi>Temple,</hi> muſt be men of more then ordinary gifts: it is not fit for ſuch who have but mean parts, to attempt to teach the learned Judges and Lawyers of the Land, who know as much as moſt men can inſtruct them: But for <hi>Eſſex</hi> was choſen Mr. <hi>Stephen Marſhal</hi> of <hi>Finchingfield.</hi> I have heard that <hi>Finchingfield</hi> is a great Benefice, and I cannot tell whether it be not as good as <hi>Bocking.</hi> But why might not Doctor <hi>Gauden</hi> as well be non-reſident as Mr. <hi>Stephen Marſhal,</hi> and preach in <hi>London,</hi> and was ſo long abſent from his Pariſh, that they petitioned the Parliament againſt him, that he might either live there with them, or leave them to chooſe another; But they could get no other anſwer from the Parliament, but they had left him to his choice; and had the times continued, he would have ſtayed upon that choice, for ought I know, until the day of his death.</p>
               <p>What you ſay of <hi>D. B.</hi> his ſecond Edition of the <hi>Tract of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge,</hi> which you think cannot be anſwered; I ſay, it is not my buſineſs now to reply to it, but I believe that if Doctor <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> hath promiſed to confute it, he will be no worſe than his word.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Others having right to ſit, were not admitted by Popular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is a moſt groſs and malicious untruth: For amongſt thoſe were choſen, and ſummoned to fit in that Aſſembly, what ſay you to Dr. <hi>Richard Love?</hi> nay what ſay you to Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> I think he ſat in the Aſſembly too, who ſuffered him to be behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Tower Hill,</hi> for endeavoring to return to his Loyalty? Dr. <hi>Ralph Browning</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Samuel Ward,</hi> Dr. <hi>John Harris,</hi> Dr. <hi>Robert Saunderſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Croſs, James</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> Dr. <hi>Matthias Styles,</hi> Dr. <hi>Featley,</hi> Dr. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Paſhly,</hi> Dr. <hi>John Hacket,</hi> Dr. <hi>Thomas Weſtfield,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> Dr. <hi>Henry Hammon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Richard Oldſworth,</hi> and many more. I ſuppoſe you named almoſt all that were worth naming, to give a handſom luſtre to the Aſſembly, and indeed there is ſcarce one of thoſe recorded here, but was worth your whole Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly beſides. I would you had ſet down a Catalogue of the reſt, I think you are aſhamed of it; but you had enough to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119177:8"/>them, and they were meetly brought thither to ſerve your turns, or elſe they ſhould have been laid aſide, as they were ſoon after. Yet he makes a confuſion in ſetting down their names, as if there were no priority and order to be taken notice of; then he demands, <hi>Where can you pick out three Biſhops more excellent for learning and piety, or other Epiſcopal Divines more able?</hi> He is ſuch a Sophiſter in this way of Queſtions, that no man can give any certain Anſwer: he ſaith thoſe fourteen were choſen and ſummoned, but whether they all ſate there, he ſaith not: and for their learning, piety and abilities, his words ſeem to imploy ſomething compared amongſt themſelves, but yet relating to the Presbyterial Divines, they were not to be compared with them.</p>
               <p>Now he hath another frolick to ſave himſelf that he be not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a lye; <hi>For of</hi> 121 <hi>Divines choſen to ſit, twenty four never appeared.</hi> And were none of thoſe you ſpeak of before, to be reckoned amongſt thoſe twenty four? it is certain if ſome of them did appear, they durſt not appear often; there were enough of them in the firſt Catalogue to have defended Epiſcopacy, if they might have had liberty, againſt all the Presbyterians in the world. It ſhould ſeem their Arguments wrought ſo eſtectually with Mr. <hi>Herbert Palmer,</hi> that he proteſted againſt Extirpation of primitive Epiſcopacy: and Doctor <hi>Burges</hi> was ſuſpended from ſitting there by the Houſe of Commons, for declaring and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting againſt the firſt Draught of the Covenant brought into the Aſſembly; for that, amongſt other things, there was required an Extirpation of Prelacy without limitation.</p>
               <p>I would fain know, to what end men late there in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly? was it to do drudgery for the Houſe of Commons, that they muſt not vote freely according to their conſcience, but they muſt be ſuſpended for ſitting there. According to this rule, ſo many carved images might have made up an Aſſembly of able Divines, if <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> might have ſitted them to be in a poſſibility to Vote as the Parliament would have them: but I doubt you have injured the Houſe of Commons, to charge them with ſuch an abſurdity; and if it be true as you ſay, you might have done well to conceal it now for both your reputations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for theſe that came not, who excluded or deter'd them? they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119177:8"/>were all ſummoned as appears by the Books of the Aſſembly; who hindred them? was it not either becauſe they liked not the Election, or the perſons choſen to ſit with them? or that being for the late King, durſt not ſit, either for fear of moleſtation by the Parlinment, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who can deſire more than this man granteth? <hi>magna eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas &amp; pravalebit:</hi> he confeſſeth that they were hindred and ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Parliament, and he knowes what popular Tumults waited upon them then, being ready at their beck to ruine, if need were, all that did not run the ſame riſque with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the manner of Election, it was no other for his end (although more ſolemn and warrantable) then antecedanious choice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If you count canvaſſing and making of parties, and all ſiniſter ways uſed to bring things about, be more ſolemn and warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, then when every man is left to his liberty, to act according to his conſcience, then you are right.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the perſons choſen to ſit with them, they were all of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be able and pious, ſo far beyond many that ſate in the uſual Convocations:</hi> were they all reputed to be ſo? by whom? <hi>wherein ſometimes Lay-men (as Chancellors and Regiſters) were admitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe Chancellors and Regiſters were admitted, that if need were, they might reſolve ſuch queſtions as ſhould ariſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Canon Law, and other things depending upon their places, that Divines were not bound not indeed could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diverting of their ſtudies of Divinity, take ſo full cognizance of: whether that were the cauſe that <hi>ſome Members of both Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſate in the laſt Aſſembly,</hi> or not rather to carry on what the deſign in hand was with a ſtronger hand, I will not undertake to reſolve.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for any fear or trouble from the Parliament, or of the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his then Majeſty, it was but a Pannick fear without ground; for being called by the Parliament, the Parliament was bound to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them:</hi> you ſaid enough before, <hi>and durſt not ſit for fear of moleſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation by the Parliament, and is it now come to be but a pannick fear without ground, and the reaſon why it is ſo, is, becauſe being called by the Parliament, the Parliament was bound to protect them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In right reaſon it ſhould be ſo, nor will I be ſo hard to accuſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119177:9"/>the Parliament, or to cenſure what they do, whether it be juſt, or no, ſome were ſo confident to affirm at the beginning of the Long-Parliament, that a Parliament can do no injuſtice. The Lawyers ſay indeed the King cannot, but whether they will ſay the ſame of the Parliament, I am not aſſured; but we will let that paſs, and ſpeak of Councels that have been held as free from error as a Parliament can be, yet you know that <hi>John Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> were ſummoned to the Councel, and had their protections from that Councel which ſummoned them, yet were they burnt for Hereticks when came there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, had they not been ſo choſen, but continued quiet, ſober, and peaceable, they needed not to fear the Parliament, witneſs that quiet, ſober, prudent Doctor</hi> Juxon <hi>Biſhop of</hi> London, <hi>who lived quietly, and without all danger of violence or impriſonment in the Parliaments Quarters, yet was he a man known to be firm to the King in the greateſt diviſions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We all grant that Doctor <hi>Juxon</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> is very quiet, ſober, prudent man, and of ſingular parts; he was ſo prudent to preſerve his own quiet, that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (as Naturaliſts write of the Bever, who knoweth wherefore, he is hunted) to leave all he had for a prey to you; and 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable many others might have done, and did ſo too, yet not all; for there was a more vigilant eye upon ſome men, whom you found to be likely not long to endure your tyranny, unleſs you had them faſt lockt within your priſon Walls. Were that rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end Prelate to anſwer you now, I think he would give you but ſmall thanks for the liberty he enjoyed in the Parliaments Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>He addes, <hi>That the King was not diſpleaſed with the Biſhop of</hi> London's <hi>abode here, and therefore there could be as ltttle fear of the Kings diſpleaſure,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It is true, the Biſhop of</hi> London <hi>never ſate in the Aſſembly, becauſe not choſen a Member of it; yet the Prince</hi> Elector Palatine <hi>ſate there without offence to His Majeſty; and albeit His Ma eſty firſt diſliked the Calling and Sitting of that Aſſembly, yet afterwards he liked it, and approved of what they had done,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It is evident enough that you cared not much for the Kings
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119177:9"/>diſpleaſure, and therefore he was as good to let you do what you pleaſed, for he could not help himſelf; what you were reſolved to do, you would do without him, yet for faſhion ſake, and to delude the people, you would ask his conſent in the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way of petitioning that might be, We your Majeſties moſt humble and obedient ſubjects. As for the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>'s not being choſen, and therefore not ſitting there, it had been more trouble for him, if he had, for ſhould he have offered to croſs your faction, I ſcarce believe he ſhould have eſcaped im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, or lived ſo quietly in the Parliaments Quarters, as you ſay he did; but the Prince <hi>Elector Palatine</hi> ſate there: he did your Aſſembly a great deal of honor, but what honor he got by it himſelf, I know not: If Prince <hi>Robert</hi> and Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> might have been admitted to ſit there too, they would doubtleſs have given you great thanks for it; and they were ever ready and willing to have waired upon you, to have guarded you from all popular tumults; but you thought you were ſafer without them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>III. Propoſit on.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That notwithſtanding all that he had ſpoken touching the ſenſe of the Covenant, and ſo great a Concurence in it, he endeavoreth to vilifie, make odious, and deſtroy the Covenant it ſelf, as his main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſay he calls his anſwers <hi>oblique,</hi> and that they are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. As oblique as they are they fall directly upon you; yet ſometimes a ſlanting blow may do as much effect, as if it were down-right. He boaſteth, that he can ſhrewdly batter the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant by urging the defectiveneſs and invalidity of it to bind either in Conſcience, or in any Judicatory, becauſe without the Kings conſent, for it binds no more then the vow of a ſervant, ſon, daughter, or wife could binde them without, yea againſt the declared conſent of their maſter, father, husband under whoſe protection they were.</p>
               <p>And is not his <hi>Battering-ram</hi> as you call it, able to break your Covenant in pieces? is not this good Scripture that he quoted for it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2. how doth that <hi>make againſt him?</hi> you ſay you <hi>ſhall demonſtrate that after,</hi> but I know not when that after will be; <hi>mean while take notice that his inſtances of ſons and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119177:10"/>is a Tale of a Tubbe, there is no ſuch thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not in expreſs words you will ſay: are not conſequences drawn immediately from Scripture of any force with you? but preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is <hi>a Tale of a Tub,</hi> and he that doth uſe it is <hi>a falſe man, and not to be truſted;</hi> as if he did <hi>dare to ſalſifie an expreſs text of Scripture.</hi> The Chapter you ſay, mentions daughrers in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſes, and wives under husbands, when the Vow is made, what would you have plainer? Doth not his Argument hold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if there were not ſuch Scripture for it? Reaſon it ſelf will evince what he contends for, either in Monarchical, Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, or Aeconomical Policy: Do but judge whether it be fit for ſuch ſervants or wives to vow a Covenant without, nay againſt the conſent of thoſe under whoſe charge they are, would you be content your Relations ſhould deal ſo with you? when they are to be guided by you, to reſolve to do what they pleaſe? are you not ready to ſhake hands with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now, which you would have us to believe you are ſuch a great enemy to? you run away from them you think, and yet for want of diſcretion you run almoſt always in their mouthes. Let your wife, ſon, or daughter vow to leave you, and go into a Monaſtery, and ask a Roman Prieſt or Jeſuite whether they may do it without your conſent, and he ſhall tell you it is not in your power to hinder them, though it be againſt your expreſs prohibition. And do you not ſee now that your Covenant made without the Kings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, was firſt forged in the Popes Conſiſtory? The way you go is to make diviſions in all Countreys and Families, to cauſe all that ſhould obey, to rebel againſt their Governours. But how doth that Text make againſt Doctor <hi>Gauden?</hi> you ſay the Text ſpeaks onely <hi>of a vow made by a man,</hi> and <hi>that all ſuch vows are binding,</hi> If a man vow a vow unto the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here is not the leaſt exception, no not of a <hi>ſon under</hi> his father, but all men that vow, <hi>are by God holden unto it,</hi> whether the chief Governour <hi>conſent or not;</hi> it is onely the vow of a woman in her <hi>minority or matrimony which may be made void.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what if they vow things unlawful, &amp; contrary to the will of him who hath the rule over them, as the Covenant is ſaid to be? I underſtand not your Divinity. What if a woman being a Pagan,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119177:10"/>vow to ſerve God, who can make her Vow void? ſurely no man: ſo then the more ado you keep to juſtifie your un-warrantable Covenant, to deſtroy the Church-Government amongſt us, of which the King is, and ought to be the chief Overſeer and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, you do but hamper and intangle your ſelf the faſter: You would fain juſtifie your Covenant, though it were taken and preſt upon your fellow ſubjects, over whom I know no authority you have without the Kings conſent, is not this to wreſt the Scepter out of the Kings hand? will you make Kings like the Log you ſpeak of, which fell from <hi>Jupiter,</hi> that ſuch croaking frogs may leap upon at pleaſure? Are Kings placed by God, to let thoſe that ſhould obey, rule over them? Kings are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The Shepherds of the People: Now what if the ſheep ſhould co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to run away to the wolves, as you did, do you think it is fit for the ſhepherd to let them do it, if he can ſtop them? But you will needs make your ſelves ſupream Governors, and the King and the reſt of his ſubjects muſt be under you. But why I pray, muſt not the kings conſent be firſt ask'd &amp; obtain'd by lawful means be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you obtruded your Covenant upon his ſubjects, which was to maintain the true Proteſtant Religion and his Majeſty? was the King ſo bad a Chriſtian as not to ſuffer his ſubjects to joyn together to maintain the true Proteſtant Religion? or was he ſo careleſs of his own ſafety, that he would deny them leave to covenant for his defence? no ſuch matter. But the King ſaw the Hook, though your Bait was cunningly laid: he diſcerned the ſad and tragick Effects were like to follow it, if Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be ruined by you, &amp; would not conſent; whereupon you had no way to effect your purpoſe but by the <hi>eccho and noiſe of the times,</hi> and the midwifery of tumults and Armies. You call this <hi>notorious untruths, nothing but impudence, and therefore you will paſs through this mire without anſwering.</hi> Anſwer him indeed you cannot, and if you think to paſs through, let me tell you plainly you will ſtick faſt, and are in danger to be drowned in it; and therefore my advice is that you make haſte back again before you paſs any further.</p>
               <p>The Covenant interpreted againſt all Epiſcopacy, muſt needs grieve ſome, and pierce to the quick thoſe former lawful Oathes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119177:11"/>(where he takes it for granted, that <hi>the Covenant is not lawful:</hi> and think you that others do not take it ſo as well as he?) not onely of Allegiance and Supremacie, and Canonical obedience, but that of the King a his Corona ion, and there can be no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfetation of ſuch a cont any Vow and Covenant without appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent perjury. And what have you to ſay againſt this? You ſay ſuppoſe the Covenant were againſt all Epiſcopacy. All Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? what againſt primitive Epiſcopacy which you allow of, and think it to be Presbyterie? But what need that ſuppoſition now, if you take Epiſcopacy as it was here eſtabliſhed, which you vowed to extirpate? But you will never leave your equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. What is that to the Oath of Supremacie and Allegiance to his Majeſtie? can no man <hi>be true to Kings;</hi> but he that is for Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops? Surely it is ſomething to the Oathes of Allegiance and Supremacie, for ſubjects to rule, and to make the King ſtand for a cypher. But why to Kings? it ſeems you were ſtumbled, and would ſhift it off upon the ubjects of other Kings that have no Biſhops; but you have left it inde inite, which anſwers to a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and therefore it includes the King of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> as well as the reſt; ſo then he that takes your Covenant, cannot in that be true to Kings, that is to ſay, all Kings, unleſs he be for Biſhops; becauſe it is a Church-Government confirmed by the Kings Laws here. In other kingdoms where Biſhops are not, the caſe is not the ſame; yet I wiſh all Proteſtant Kings and Princes were ſo happy as to erect Epiſcopacy within their Dominions. The valiant King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s reſolution was when the <hi>Swede</hi> beſieged <hi>Copenhagen</hi> (if I rightly underſtand the meaning of what I read) that he then promiſed, that if it pleaſed God to give him the Victory, he would make his Scholars bear their proportion with his Nobles, I can give it no other interpretation but ſerting up of Lords Biſhops in his countrey. But as for the kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> you know what King <hi>James</hi> ſpake prophetically, <hi>No Biſhop, no King;</hi> and it proved too true, for no ſooner were my Lords the Biſhops caſt down, and the Archbiſhop beheaded, but immediately it fell ſore upon the King himſelf, even to the loſs of his life, though the Covenant ran for his preſervation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> 
                  <q>Doubtleſs the ſenſe of the Covenant hath lately quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119177:11"/>many mens coſciences in their Allegiance to the King, ſo to bring him (as <hi>David</hi>) home with infince joy and triumph.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I think the Doctor hath pleaſed you now, for you grow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently very high in your own commen ſacion <hi>Who acted moſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>introducing the ſecluded Members, in procuring a free Parliament, ara in bringing home His preſent Majeſty (whom God bleſs and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve)</hi> and let all the people ſay Ameny <hi>but Covenanters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But was this the fruit of your Covenane? we know what effect it had upon his ſo mer Majeſty <hi>Charles</hi> the I. can the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing forth bitter water and ſweet? We know God drawes light out of darkneſs, and makes uſe or contrary means ſometimes to bring about his purpoſes: By accident the Covenant hath made many deluded men more ſenſible of their duty, but I cannot finde that it wrought any thing directly to the Kings preſervation and eſtabliſhment, more then the Jewes murthering our bleſſed Savior obliged all men to be thankful to them for mans Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption: where then is the Blaſphemy to be abhorred of all ſober Chriſtians, in ſaying the <hi>Covenant</hi> is contradictory to former oaths?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Touching the Oaths of Canonical Obedience to Biſhops, they took upon them to impoſe ſuch a tyrannical yoke upon many of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> ſed quo jure, <hi>and how far were ſuch Oathes obl gatory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhops took no more upon them in this, than they had authority from the Kings and Parliaments, (whatſoever you ſay to the contrary) and that is right enough: (it will be too long to fearch Antiquities for Oathes Canonical, uſed in the primitive times, and to compare them with this) and therefore ſuch Oathes are as obligatory as other Oathes are; and had your Covenant been ſo eſtabliſhed, what would you have ſaid for it then, that ſay ſo much for it now, that all other Oathes muſt give place to it? The Oath of obedience to the Dioceſan, which many of you in Orders have taken, is wilfully broken by you: why do you not renounce your Orders to which you received from the Biſhops, and be ordained again after your new model? You think to lick your ſelves clean with ſuch pitiful ſhifts as theſe, pretending your Covenant to be ſacred and obligatory, as if it were another Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladium, the image that fell from <hi>Juniter,</hi> your great <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that you, like <hi>Demetrius,</hi> plead ſo ſtrongly for, ſeeing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119177:12"/>your Craft is in danger to be ſet at nought, and your <hi>Diana</hi> to be deſtroyed, whoſe magnificence you would have to be worſhipped by the Chriſtian world? Yet I know not why you ſhould quarrel with the Biſhops Oath, which you grant requires obedience onely <hi>in licitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> you ſay is needleſs, <hi>becauſe the Laws tye men to things lawful and honeſt:</hi> By this reaſon all Oaths are needleſs, for no Oaths ought to be made, but for to binde mens obedience in things lawful and honeſt. Had your Covenant been onely ſo, we would not have made a queſtion about it. You ſay the Doctor hath furniſhed you with an Argument ſtrong enough to retort upon himſelf, by which he argues the needleſneſs of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and ſo do you the <hi>unwarranted</hi> Oath of Canonical Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; you band it upon him, and it flies back in your own face.</p>
               <p>If this Oath ſhould be extended to obey ſuch Biſhops as <hi>Wren</hi> and <hi>Pieroe,</hi> as you unreverently ſtyle them without their due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor you owe unto them and others, in all they late enjoyned, what have you to ſay againſt thoſe reverend Prelates and others? not one word as I finde here but a flouriſh of your own, as if you had ſome greater matters againſt them, and then inferre, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of them you have more cauſe your Covenant <hi>be extended to extirpation of all Epiſcopacy, and ſo farewel ſuch an Oath:</hi> nay, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther farewel ſuch a Covenant, that there is more reaſon for it to be aboliſhed for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Touching the Kings Oath, there is nothing obliging him further than to preſerve that Government, ſo far as it is agreeable to, and warranted by the holy Scripture and primitive Inſtitution, ſo far he condeſcended at the Iſle of</hi> Wight, <hi>and who requires more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſay ſo too, who requireth more? ſo far do all the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal party condeſcend with him, and you are forced to yield to it: wherefore let me tell you, and I hope His Majeſty that now is will not be offended if I ſpeak my conſcience in it, that it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honourable, ſafe, nor lawful for Him to break this Oath of His Coronation; nor indeed can it be diſanulled, but there muſt follow a wonderful and dangerous metamorphoſis in the whole frame of the Government of <hi>England.</hi> I ſhall give you my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for all this, when you can pretend any thing that hath but the ſhew of Reaſon, Law, or Religion againſt it. Though you ſay
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119177:12"/>this alſo may be changed by His Royal Aſſent to the counſel and deſire of the two Houſes of Parliament, as this Doctor doth more then tacitely admit. How more then tacitely doth the Doctor admit it? I believe it is no more but your own fancy: But we hope the two Houſes will never counſel, nor deſire any ſuch thing, and if they ſhould, you know that King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt would never yield His Royal Aſſent, and I know not why you ſhould look for more from King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. who will doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs make uſe of his pious Fathers Advice to Him in His <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? and it were not Chriſtian like for you to attempt to divert him from it. But where hath His Majeſty and His two Houſes been theſe many years, to do it? the way you propound to change it, was not to be had, and I believe never ſhould have been if you could have helpt it: you had a ſhorter cut by your Covenant, to effect it without the Royal Aſſent and Upper-Houſe, for you would have none; and I cannot tell how you like it now.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cannot the Legiſlative Power change Government by Biſhops, as well as abrogate other Laws?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is to charge ſome with perjury whom he dares not name, to fright others with men of clouts, and to condemn all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt which have laid Epiſcopacy aſide. Hath the Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative Power ſuch Authoritie, and yet may not abrogate your Covenant, but it muſt be like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> that alter not? No Royal Aſſent, nor two Houſes muſt meddle with that, but you ſcare all with bug-bears, and men of clouts, pretending that God will revenge the breach of that, and yet you break the reſt and fear no revenge, as if your Covenant were another Pope that can abſolve you from them all. We know it is proper for Parliaments to abrogate and alter ſuch Lawes as are not good and uſeful. Who I pray doth this charge with per-jury, that the Doctor ſhould fear to name? But Epiſcopacie is not to be numbred amongſt things unlawful or uſeleſs, that it ſhould be abrogated to bring in your Presbytery in the place, which is ten times worſe. The errors and evils Epiſcopacy lieth open to, are not more not greater than Presbytery hath, and the benefits of it are infinitely beyond yours. Lot the Presbyters
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119177:13"/>draw up a Liſt of all they can object againſt Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and back what they ſay by Scripture, good Authority, by Reaſon and Examples, and we ſhall draw the parallel againſt Presbytery, and then let every man be judge which of the two hath moſt cauſe to be covenanted againſt: and if they pleaſe to enumerate the Benefits of their Presbyterial Government, we ſhall do the like for Biſhops, the work would be large, and worth the while to be undertaken, to reconcile the Differences in Church Diſcipline, and to give better ſatisfaction to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world. I ſhall now, to avoid prolixtry ſpeak a word or two only of the benefits of Epiſcopacy; for the faults it is obnoxious to, are not eſſential to the Government, but meerly accidental.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, it is more orderly, regular, and uniform, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence more free from ſchiſms, ſects, hereſies, and whatſoever miſchief may gather to a head for want of good order. 2. It is more decent, graceful, and more conſiſtent with Monarchy: a poor creeping Clergy is not comely in Chriſtian Princes Courts, who will ſeem always to upbraid them to their faces, as if they were not willing to be at any coſt for the preaching of the Goſpel; whereas the beſt Kings and Emperors, as <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius,</hi> and others, ſought ſtill how with rich endowments to beautifie and adorn them. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt be together, the King and the Prieſt, the Crown and the Miter, the Princes Scepter and the Biſhops Croſier, or elſe the Scepter will be ſoon made to ſtoop to the Presbyterian Ferula. 3. It is greater encouragement to Learning and Religion: Take away the reward of Vertue, and you do what you can to take away Goodneſs itſelf: <hi>Pramia ſi tollas, tollitur virtus;</hi> but I muſt not let my pen run to a volumn, 4. Conſider that many Reformed Churches are in miſery, and ready to be ſwallowed up continually by Popiſh and cruel Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, what can the Presbyterian party do to afford them any help? ſurely little or none; whereas when our Church flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en under the Biſhops, the Proteſtants abroad in all places lived in more repoſe and quiet, and found continual aſſiſtance from them inſomuch that their foes did hardly dare to make any head againſt them: and I doubt not but they will conreſs how ſenſible they have been ſince theſe troubles, of the great loſs they have of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119177:13"/>Prelacy in <hi>England,</hi> by whoſe warineſs and continual care of them, as well as of their charge at home, they were always foſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and preſerved ſince the Reformation. What horrid perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have fallen upon them ſince the expelling of our Biſhops here, let the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> and the poor Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants living about the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> whom the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and others endeavored with all their might to take away from the earth, ſpeak. The like cruelties were uſed lately upon the Reformed Cantons in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> alſo in <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and the French Proteſtants fearing daily to be rooted out, and what remedy could they ſinde with you? I will not ſpeak too bad of the great Collections made by you here for them, and how they were employed for their relief. Alſo of the monſtrous blaſphemies, damned hereſies, ſhameful adulteries, and many other villanies which have ſprung up ſince Presbytery bore the ſway, the names whereof were ſcarcely known when Epiſcopacy ruled. Let ſome more able pen proceed.</p>
               <p>And however ſome Churches of Chriſt expelling Popery, in heat of zeal have thereby laid lawful Epiſcopacy aſide, that is, have not had ſince the opportunity to reſtore it to its primitive Inſtitution, yet many of them deſire to conform to the plat-form of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which they ſuppoſe to come the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of any to the Apoſtolick form.</p>
               <p>His next quarrel is:<q>If the Covenant abjure all Epiſcopacy, it runs upon a rock of novelty and ſchiſm, and daſheth us in opinion and practice againſt the judgement and cuſtom of the Catholick Church in all Ages and places (till of latter years) from the Apoſtles days.</q>
               </p>
               <p>You call <hi>this a Magiſterial and traditional way:</hi> Surely ſuch traditions as theſe are not to be under-valued, the Hiſtories and Monuments of the Church are a great light to us in many things, eſpecially ſuch as are circumſtancial, and without them we ſhould wander in the dark.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But once prove that your abol ſhed Epiſcopacy was of ſo ancient and univerſal obſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Aboliſhed we praiſe God you cannot ſay, but that you did your beſt to aboliſh it, the antiquity of it hath been often proved to your ſhame.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119177:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoever ſhall read the Judgement of Dr.</hi> John Reynolds <hi>concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Epiſcopacy, expreſſed in a Letter to Sir</hi> Francis Knolls, <hi>and Dr.</hi> Uſhers Reduction, <hi>will finde this mans bold aſſertion, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have not means nor opportunity to ſee that Letter, nor any of his Quotations: but I remember when I was a Scholar in <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> whereof ſome years before Doctor <hi>John Reynolds</hi> had been Preſident, I was told he was once much given to be a Roman Catholick, and that his brother a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant converted him, whom I knew in <hi>Gloceſter</hi>-Hall, but he fell ſhortly after himſelf to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein he died: now though Doctor <hi>Reynolds</hi> was a very learned and pious man, who by a kinde of Antiperiſtaſis becauſe of his brothers fall, might be more violent againſt the Diſcipline of our Church, than perhaps otherwiſe he would have been; yet he met with as pious and learned men as himſelf at the Conference at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, 2 King <hi>James,</hi> that maintained it, and carried it againſt him and all that were of his judgement. The ſame cauſe that provoked Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> may be, prevailed with an eminent perſon in this Land to favour your Covenanters ſo much at firſt, becauſe his brother was revolted to Popery; But this was not the Biſhops fault, it had been more honorable for them both to have followed the example of their Reverend Uncle <hi>James,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> Prelate of the Garter, and my moſt honored Patron during my minority, who knew better how to direct in Church affairs than they ever did: but for want of his Compaſs they ran a great hazard, to fall upon thoſe two dangerous Rocks that lay on either hand, of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Presbytery.</hi> As for Dr. <hi>Uſhers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,</hi> if that be the meaning of it, we grant it is not held fit that the Biſhops ſhould keep too great a diſtance, and eſtrange themſelves too much from their brethren: it is acknowledged to have been a fault in ſome of them, and it is proper it ſhould be amended. But pray give me leave to referre you to Dr. <hi>Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams Defence of Epiſcopacy,</hi> and when you can anſwer him, I ſhall ſay that you have anſwered the Doctor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Under colour of propounding the loy land religious ſenſe of it, he daſheth it with unlawfulneſs to be taken at all, becauſe not impoſed by due Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119177:14"/>
               <p>This hath been ſo often repeated, that it is <hi>crambe ſaepius cocta,</hi> and needs no anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> 
                  <q>The Jews ſometimes ſolemnly renewed their Covenant with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which God himſelf had made with them in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reb</hi> and mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> punctually preſcribed to God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and by <hi>Moſes</hi> (as the ſupream Governor or King) impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; but this was not the caſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor was there need of ſuch a Covenant, or any <hi>Moſes, &amp;c.</hi> as chief Governor commanding it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here you keep a fearful quoil and whiffle about, making a great cry, but there is little wooll, calling the Doctor <hi>Deceiver, Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler;</hi> and that in his Writings there <hi>are falſhoods enough,</hi> and yet ſhew none. Firſt you ſay it <hi>is falſe</hi> that there was no Covenant but of Gods <hi>own</hi> preſcribing: and ſecondly that he <hi>preſcribed</hi> but one. I do not finde that the Doctor ſaith any ſuch thing; for ho quoted that ſpontaneous Vow, <hi>Numb</hi> 30.2. You are ſtill fighting with your own ſhadow, yet you muſt ſay ſomething, leſt the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould think you were at a <hi>non-plus,</hi> as Sergeant <hi>Green</hi> did, who would undertake to overthrow all Epiſcopacy, but being worſted by the learned <hi>Selden,</hi> cryed out, <hi>But Archbiſhops are no Biſhops;</hi> then ſaid <hi>Selden, Judges are no Lawyers,</hi> and <hi>Aldermen no Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</hi> You inſtance in the Covenant of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Princes of the Congregation, with the cheating Gibeonites, as you call them, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.15. But there was <hi>Moſes</hi> the chief, whoſe conſent you never had, and therefore are leſs excuſable than the Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites were. But becauſe you are ſo much taken with the Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites example, and bring it in ſo often, as if it ſerved your turn well, I ſhall ſay more to it, when I meet with it again.</p>
               <p>The chief Covenant indeed was that which God made with his people upon mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and all lawfull Covenants which man makes with God are but branches of that, as when we renew our obedience by ſerious repentance, as the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the children of <hi>Judah</hi> did, vowing to keep Gods Commandments. But I know not that God gave you any ſuch command to vow againſt Epiſcopacy, and I doubt you never asked his counſel when you entred into it, what ever your heady zeal might ſuggeſt to you; for it is not a good intention, (fi we may be ſo charitable as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119177:15"/>to think you intended no harm it) that makes a good action; but you muſt have ſufficient warrant for it from Gods word, ſhew but that, and we have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is falſe that the Covenant was impoſed by</hi> Moſes, <hi>or that</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>was ſupream Governor; for</hi> Moſes <hi>was no more ſupream Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or King than</hi> Samuel.</p>
               <p>You love to move queſtions: <hi>Samuel</hi> no doubt whileſt he was the ſole Judge over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was their ſupream Governour until <hi>Saul</hi> was anointed King. But <hi>Samuel</hi> was never in Scripture called King as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, as <hi>King in Jeſurun.</hi> The like blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering he keeps, <hi>who impoſed the Covenant of the Law, God or</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? Doubtleſs God principally, but miniſterially it was done by the hand of <hi>Moſes:</hi> this is to amuſe his Covenanters, and ſuch as will be taken with ſhadows; for what of all this? here is great ſtir to little purpoſe, unleſs you wil conclude aright as you ſhould do: the King in his kingdom is next under God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> amongſt the Iſraelites, and his ſubjects muſt be guided &amp; directed by him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He bleſſeth God as one would bleſs an idol:</hi> 
                  <q>That Apoſtacy to ſtrange gods was not the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> caſe, that they ſhould enter into a Covenant.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tell me what meant the falling off of ſeveral Biſhops to too much Popery in doctrine, witneſs all their Arminian Tenents, and alſo their general practice in Cathedrals, and elſewhere, ſeiting up Altars, Tapers, Candles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>deviſed by mans fancies; which laſt is, (with many other things) in the Queens Injunctions,</hi> Injunct. 3. <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to tend to idolatry and ſuperſtition,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the like may be ſaid of Church Muſick Anthems,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>a thing which the judicious</hi> Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <hi>cenſured and condemned, and the late Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt,</hi> Injunct. 49. <hi>and if any Hymn were ſung, care muſt be taken that it be ſo done, as to be underſtood and perceived, and where this is not ſo done, ſee the Cenſure of the</hi> Homily <hi>of the place and time of Prayer,</hi> Part 2.</p>
               <p>To anſwer to every particular would require a large volumn; but you have anſwered your ſelf, and juſtified the Doctor, that Apoſtacy to ſtrange gods, was not the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Caſe. You quote judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> condemning ſomething; let him be the Umpire, if you pleaſe, between the Biſhops and the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119177:15"/>and you ſay Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Injunctions have made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion againſt ſuch things; and the Books of <hi>Homilies</hi> condemns other things: well, what would you have then? you ſee there is good proviſion made againſt all exorbitancies in Ceremonies, and the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is comprehended in the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> if any man have tranſgreſſed, and done more then he can anſwer, he is lyable to be queſtioned for it; and I think ſo may you for your contempt, and covenanting contrary to all former Laws or Examples, only what you have labored to procure ſince for your own ſecurity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for Popiſh families crept into</hi> England, <hi>with ſwarms of Prieſts and Jeſuites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There have more crept in ſince theſe civil Wars began with your Covenant, than ever were ſince the Reformation, yet you would charge all upon the Biſhops. The Lawes made againſt Prieſts and Jeſuits were they put in practice, were good enough; and had there been as good proviſion made againſt your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting, it had bin well for the Church of <hi>England.</hi> You are very pettiſh, becauſe the Doctor ſpeaks what others believe to be true, that the Covenant was but the petty compoſition of a few poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lawyers or Miniſters, no great Clerks or States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> adding, that their heads rather than their hearts, and State-correſpondencies more than their Conſciences brought it forth: we finde a great deal of pretended zeal in it, but he that ſhall uſe St. <hi>Pauls</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and hold it againſt the Sun, ſhall quickly perceive many flaws and foul ſpots that it hath, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the rottenneſs of their hearts, the idleneſs of their heads that made it, by muſtering up clean and unclean together, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no difference betwixt things lawful, and thoſe that are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Law of God.</p>
               <p>The Doctor ſaid, <q>There is no pattern for any ſuch Covenant in the New Teſtament nor in all ſucceeding ages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> no Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting Chriſtians until the holy League,</q> (<hi>meaning, ſay you, that of the bloody Papiſts to deſtrey the</hi> Hugonots, ſo they termed the Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> that is but an ill preſident for you to follow:) <q>except that of Baptiſm, the new and Evangelical Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of all true Chriſtians.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119177:16"/>
               <p>You anſwer, <hi>If there were no Precept nor Pattern in the New Teſtament, it is ſufficient if there be any in the Old; if not Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical or meerly typical, unleſs the Doctor be turned An inomian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wiſh you were as ſound in both Teſtaments as the Doctor is. The Evangelical Covenant of Baptiſm in the New Teſtament is <hi>vaſtly different</hi> indeed from your Scorch Covenant; that hath made ſuch a rent in the Church for the devil and all his works to enter by, againſt which we covenanted in Baptiſm; and being you can finde no ſhelter for it in the New Teſtament, you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Old; and there you are in as bad a caſe, for unleſs you will make uſe of <hi>Korah</hi> and his Conſpiracy, I know not what precept or pattern you finde for it, for you produce none: onely you make a queſtion, <hi>Is there no precept nor pattern for covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt our Engliſh Epiſcopacy?</hi> and you make your own an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>(There is not any for it I ſay) nor is it much material that he hath found none againſt it; for we can finde no ſuch Epiſcopacy in the New Teſtament, nor warranted by it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we can finde patterns of Epiſcopacy both in the Old and New Teſtament, that were not barely typical, but an excellent form of Church-Government by High Prieſts, Prieſts, and Levites, by the apoſtles extraordinary, in whoſe room our ordinary Biſhops ſucceeded, under whom were the 70. the Presbyters in a large ſenſe ſometimes called Biſhops alſo, and under them the Deacons. This is as clear from the New Teſtament as noon day, in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Timothy, &amp;c.</hi> and he muſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhut his eyes that ſees not the diſtinction of theſe Offices in the Church, which continued from the primitive times, until this late Covenanting way pat the Church of God into a confuſion, and ſought to deſtroy all order and uniformity; and I think they are no little proud of it, that without either Precept or Pattern were the firſt inventers of it, and would fain propagate it to future times, but I hope they will be deceived; for it hath coſt men ſo dear already, that it is probable they will take warning, and learn to be wiſer hereafter. We have ſhewed you ground enough for eſtabliſhing Epiſcopacy, ſhew us as much if you can, for your Piesb terial Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Covenant is not onely againſt his adored Epiſcopacy, but in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119177:16"/>the full latitude extended againſt Popery, hereſie, ſchiſm, &amp;c.</hi> (how chance then you break it by being ſo ſchiſmatical?) <hi>profaneneſs, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound doctrine, &amp;c. and for Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reformation of Religion, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its well you put Preſervation firſt, and we wiſh you had done ſo, for where you begin to reſorm you deſtroy all, witneſs your information of the Liturgy, caſting it quite out of doors: You ſay <hi>it was not made onely againſt Epiſcopacy;</hi> but it was princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, as if that were worſe then Popery; for you muſt it ſeemes ſtretch it in its full latitude to take in Popery, hereſie, or any thing elſe; and had it not been that Epiſcopacy ſtood in your way, which you knew not how to remove, your Covenant had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been made againſt any of the reſt, or elſe ſurely you would, as there was always cauſe enough, have entred into it long before: but Popery, hereſie, ſchiſm, and all that you were pleaſed to make to depend upon Epiſcopacy in the Covenant, were onely added to perſwade the people who underſtood no better, that Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was the foundation of them all. You have put in alſo many ſweet ingredients to make it go down the better: <hi>to maintain true Religion.</hi> You have maintained it fairly. <hi>Defence of His Majeſties perſon.</hi> And did you not well defend him? <hi>Ad populum phaleras.</hi> And why are you ſo offended with the Doctor, to <hi>throw off and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominate the Covenant meerly for onely one ſingle Clauſe for extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the late Hierarchy, if ſo intended?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You did intend it ſure enough, and therefore is that ſingle Clauſe ſufficient; were it not ſafer to throw the Covenant away than to take it, when the poiſon lies cloſe in it is diſcovered? Speak I pray you, or elſe let ſome men of more reaſon and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion anſwer for you. For the Doctor to <hi>deſor be particularly what Epiſcopacy he would have retroduced,</hi> I think you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his meaning, or let me tell you, ſuch as it was before your Covenant drove it out, onely with this limitation, that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mens errors ſhould not be imputed to the Government which allows them not, but declaims againſt them. You ſay <hi>you might leave it to all ſober Chriſtians, how little your Covenant differs from the Covenant of Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>wherein every man ſtipulateth to deny all ungodlineſs, and to live ſoberly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119177:17"/>
               <p>If you will leave it ſo, I am certain you will be condemned by them for it, for they were no ſober Chriſtians that penned the Covenant, but hot-ſpurs and fiery zealots, who will force all men to be guided by what they pleaſe to ſet up, as <hi>Nebuchadaezar</hi> did his golden image, that every man muſt fall down and worſhip it: do you ſay how little your Covenant differs from the ſacred Covenant of Baptiſm? You gave that Epithere <hi>Sacred</hi> to your Covenant before, and do you th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk they are ſo much of a kinde becauſe of that? they differ <hi>toto coelo,</hi> they are no more like, as the Proverb is, than chalk and cheeſe, and I believe I may ſafely call it <hi>blaſphemy</hi> to compare the factious Contrivances of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious men, to Gods ſacred Ordinances. And what you inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning the Baptiſmal Covenant to ſtrengthen yours, is but vain babling, for it ſignifies nothing to any underſtanding man.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Do true Chriſtians truly entred in o the Baptiſmal Covenant, break it by wilful and preſumptuous ſins?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe the Doctor ſaid, we break our Covenant in Baptiſm by wilful and preſumptuous ſins, did you never ſin wilfully ſince you were baptized? is all weakneſſes with you? who I might ſay have wilfully and maliciouſly contrary to Gods Law, fallen away from your due obedience to your Governors, and erected a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a Calf in <hi>Horeb,</hi> to make your ſelves famous amongſt the congregation, and to exalt your ſelves above your Superiors, <hi>you take too much upon you, ye ſons of</hi> Levi.</p>
               <p>You ſay you have <hi>inſiſted upon this the longer, becauſe of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors words,</hi> That by repentance we renew our Covenant in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: <hi>ſurely,</hi> ſay you, <hi>no more then it renews the remiſſion of our ſins, which no repentance but Chriſt in Baptiſm hath beſtowed upon us once for all.</hi> Thus you trifle away the time by ſiniſter interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of what will admit a very ſafe and Orthodox conſtruction; for without Chriſts merits all Baptiſm and Repentance is of none effect; yet you have a very acute noſe that you can ſmell here a ſtrong ſavour of Arminianiſm and Popery. I ſhall make amends by <hi>brevity in the reſt:</hi> You need not have croubled us with ſo much idle diſcourſe as you have done.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Doctor ſaith, That there is neither Law of God or man requiring, or comprobating any ſuch Covenant, at the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119177:17"/>beſt it is but a matter of Will-worſhip, of human, private inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> an Engine framed of purpoſe to batter down Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to ſeize their Eſtates, and the Church-patrimony, to the great enrichment of ſome ſacrilegious Proteſtants, to the great joy of the Romiſh party and Jeſuits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who were thought to be, if not the <hi>Sires</hi> of it, yet the <hi>Sibs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſay it is ſo full of rayling, that no wiſe man will hold it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than folly to beſtow a line in anſwering to it. If this be not blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, I know not what is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is in vain for you to attempt to anſwer it, for you never can, who call that which is the manifeſt Truth, and you know it well enough, <hi>Blaſphemy:</hi> having indeed nothing to ſay againſt it, you are galled, and kick, and fling terribly, and are forced to ſhuffle off the buſineſs again to Dr. <hi>Burges, whoſe Book,</hi> you ſay, <hi>making it out that it is no ſacriledge to buy ſuch Lands, ſtill lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwered:</hi> but you ſay further, Dr. <hi>G. hath promiſed it,</hi> and then you may not doubt but it will be anſwered. But did any of you buy them of the Biſhops? that had bin ſome qualification to your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, but you took them by force from them, and then ſold them to one another; and would have men believe it is ſo far from ſacriledge, that you will not admit that it is any ſin at all.</p>
               <p>But whereas the Doctor ſaith, This Age is the firſt Parent of that Prodigy, wherein Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians, either Presbyters or people did perſecute Godly Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea and Epiſcopacy it ſelf. You deny <hi>that any Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>did perſecute any Godly Biſhops of this age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That many of our Biſhops were Godly, you cannot deny, for you ſay afterwards <hi>that no doubt but ſome of thoſe Biſhops which he commendeth, were learned and pious:</hi> And all know that they were ſeverely proſecuted, plundered, and impriſoned by you, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them perſecuted unto death, for the troubles they endured doubtleſs ſhortned their days. I would I had by me a perfect Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of them to ſet down, that the Reader might be his own Judge; but it is yet ſo freſh in memory, that every man almoſt will ſay you ſpeak a great untruth to deny it: yet I believe you, they were no Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians did it, but rather Jews, Turks, Infidels, and yet it is poſſible ſuch would have ſhew'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119177:18"/>them more mercy. You <hi>grant it is true, that ſome Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians did exhibit and proſecute Archbiſhop</hi> Laud, <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> Wren, <hi>and Biſhop</hi> Pierce; <hi>two, if not all of them, being charged with no leſs than high Treaſon, the firſt whereof being found guilty, was executed</hi> Jan. 10. 1644. Were they Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians that did exhibit and proſecute, how do you prove that? and as for your high Treaſon, you made any thing high Treaſon that you pleaſed to call ſo in your High Courts of Injuſtice: you know it is not the charging any man that makes him guilty; to ſay nothing of many eminent loyal ſubjects that ſuffered in the ſame cauſe. Was not his ſacred Majeſty <hi>Charles</hi> the I. of bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory charged, proſecuted, condemned, and executed, for that you call High Treaſon, by the ſame power that ruled? was He therefore guilty, what ſay you? As for the Archbiſhop, becauſe there are others better able to write in his defence than I am, I ſhall paſs it by, leaving him and his proſecutors and Judges to the moſt righteous Judge of heaven and earth. <hi>But the other two never anſwered the Articles exhibited againſt them to this day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray whoſe fault was that? was not the reverend Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Wren</hi> kept in priſon by you 14 or 15 years, and never ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to come to his Anſwer? which is argument ſufficient to prove him not guilty, and your ſelves to be cruel and barbarous, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, contrary to law, reaſon, or conſcience, had not then Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> cauſe to plead as an <hi>Advocate</hi> in his behalf, ſince doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he hath been exceedingly injured by you? who endured it with much Chriſtian patience, being not brought to his Trial, but kept priſoner, that upon any emergent occaſion, when you knew not how to go on, you might bring him forth to ſacrifice him, to appeaſe the fury of the people? how would you have cried out at perſecution, if the Biſhops had ſerved any of you ſo? but they are of a nobler minde, and abhor ſuch cruelty.</p>
               <p>You ſay again, <hi>When Dr.</hi> Gauden'<hi>s hand was in, he beſtowes a Vindication or Apology upon a known Papiſt, the late Biſhop of</hi> Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter, <hi>Dr.</hi> Goodman.</p>
               <p>I have not ſeen that Apologie, but I am perſwaded Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> is a Gentleman of that wiſdom and integrity, that he will give you or any man elſe a good account of what he hath ſaid of him.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119177:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But he could finde nothing to ſay for Dr.</hi> Pierce, <hi>who ſo devontly thanked God he had put down all the Locturers in his Dioceſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I may believe your report, for your tongue is no ſlander, the Doctor could have found enough to ſay for him; for it is well known Lord Biſhop <hi>Pierce,</hi> who was Vice-chancellor of <hi>Oxford</hi> in my time, was held to be as Orthodox and able a Preacher, as moſt in the Univerſity; and if he did give God thanks for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down Lecturers in his Dioceſs, I preſume it was becauſe the people grew ſo head-ſtrong and diſorderly, that they brought in Lecturers, not ſo much to hear them preach the word of God, as to oppoſe their Parſons, and to raiſe ſchiſms and factions in their Pariſhes: but no ſober and quiet Orthodox Miniſter was, or would have been hindred by him, or any of the other Biſhops, from following his calling, and from preaching the Goſpel; yet if any were hindred, it was not the Biſhops fault that they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: but to make uſe of your words, <hi>it was the other ruffling violent Ringleaders that were the cauſe of it,</hi> who were adored by the vulgar, as the Barbarians did St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and were ready almoſt to ſay of them that they were Gods, ſacrificing all they had in feaſting them, until many families were undone by them; you are not aſhamed to deride our learned Biſhops reverend for their age, by the name of <hi>Old Epiſcopalians,</hi> what were your Lecturers many of them, but young beardleſs Boys of 16 or 17 years old, more fit to have been whipt at ſchool, or to be prieſts to <hi>Jupiter</hi> or <hi>Bacchus,</hi> then Teachers of the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let him name one of thoſe Biſhops, unleſs it were ſuch as were tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan'd by</hi> Williams, <hi>and other caprisious Pragmaticks, to have their hands in that high and un-Parlamentary Petition and Proreſtation to the late King and Houſe of Peers,</hi> 1641. <hi>that were in the leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and not rather ſavoured (if indeed learned and godly) by Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians, either Presbyters or people. If any of thoſe ſuffered with the reſt, they may thank thoſe ruffling, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonious</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and not blame others who could not help it, nor longer endure the ſlavery and perſecution thoſe</hi> Amaziah-<hi>like Prieſts and Tyrants had exereiſed over them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they were under perſecution all the time your Power la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted is moſt certain, witneſs that famous Divine, the Reverend
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119177:19"/>Doctor <hi>Featley,</hi> and others of great worth, but that they who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted them were Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians I cannot grant, rather wolves and tygers, men void of humanity, and much more of Chriſtian Piety. But you have ſuch fine acute ways to play ſaſt and looſe, and to ſhuffle oft a Charge, unleſs thoſe that were perſecuted, (you grant there was a perſecution) were ſuch as <hi>were trapann'd by</hi> Williams, <hi>(if they were indeed learned and godly) if any of thoſe ſuffered with the reſt, they may thank their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows:</hi> but you ſpared no ſuch men as you except here, for thoſe ſuffered moſt that were the moſt pious, and of greateſt wiſdom and learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their eminent parts were the greateſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle to your growing deſigns; if any of them ſtood in your way they muſt become the objects of your fury, who had ſuch tender conſciences, that rather than fail of your aim, the beſt muſt ſuffer with the worſt, and you ſpared none though you knew them to be perſons of great deſert, which are onely hypothetically excepted by you. Who then, I pray you, were the <hi>Amaziah</hi>-like Prieſts and Tyrants, your Presbyters, or our Biſhops, who were men of nobler ſpirits, and ſcorn'd and abhorr'd ſuch unreaſonable and un-chriſtian proceedings? But why are you ſo much diſpleaſed with the Lord Biſhop <hi>Williams,</hi> a man long ſince dead, and mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre all your envy, died peaceably in his own countrey? what you ſpeak of his trapanning, it is well known it was not uſed here in <hi>England,</hi> until you trapann'd the whole Nation by your new Covenant, but I know where your ſhoe rings you. It is that <hi>un-Parliamentary Petition and Proteſtation,</hi> ſo you call it, that he had the chiefeſt hand in, and a great many more honeſt cordial Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops as well as himſelf. This gallant Perſon hath obliged all the Clergy of the three Nations by this memorable Act, to have a good opinion of his Loyalty to the King; had the Biſhops then held their peace for fear or favour, their ſilence would have been interpreted conſent; and I know not what they could have pleaded now in defence of their Baronies, and for their reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the Upper Houſe of Parliament, that we may once more have, as it ought to be, Lords Spiritual and Temporal: I ſpeak not to the honor of that reverend Prelate, as if I meant to ſet forth a Panegyrick of his Gallantry, for any favor or benefit I was obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119177:19"/>to him for, I may truly ſay I was never more beholding to him than I was to the reſt, but I deſire to give every man his due character; had he not been a Perſon of great learning, and noble parts, ſurely King <hi>James,</hi> ſo wiſe a Prince, would never have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to ſo great preferment in Church and State. How he came to fall into diſgrace with ſome great Perſons, I cannot ſay; but I believe it was by his too much leaning to that totten Prop of Presbytery, hoping thereby to ſupport himſelf againſt thoſe who laid violent ſiege to his honor and preferment, and as it is conjectured by ſome, to his life alſo; which fierce diſſentions amongſt the Biſhops themſelves, and the Clergy that ſided with their diviſions, made ſuch breaches in the Church, that the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters entred upon them, and had well-nigh routed them all: but the beſt and learnedſt men in the world are ſubject to failings, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> were divided, which make them the leſs able to reſiſt the common enemy. I hope it wil be a warning to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhops to take care to agree as brethren among themſelves</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>IV. Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That, maugre all this mans calumnies, and malicious aſperſions, the Covenant (even as to the point of Hierarchical Epiſcopacy lately laid aſide) is to be conſtantly and conſcientiouſly obſerved and kept in the right ſenſe thereof, by all that have taken it, as they will avoid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and damnation hereafter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſhould appear that the Presbyterians finde it beſt fiſhing in troubled waters: they mean (it ſeems) that we ſhall never be at peace in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for all thoſe that have taken their Covenant, are bound <hi>conſtantly and conſcientiouſly</hi> to obſerve and keep it <hi>in the right ſenſe thereof,</hi> (that is, as he hath interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it all this while, <hi>to the extirpation of Epiſcopal Hierarchy) as they will avoid deſtruction here:</hi> deſtruction here, this ſmells ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſome miſchief hatching by them againſt us, <hi>and damnation hereafter.</hi> I pray God they do not fall into the pit themſelves, which they are digging for others: but if ſome muſt fall into it, we ſhall pray in the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Let them fall into their own net together, and let us ever eſcape them.</hi> They that <hi>have taken it,</hi> muſt you ſay, <hi>conſtantly keep it,</hi> and what muſt, or will they do that have not taken it? do you ſuppoſe they will let you domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119177:20"/>over them? they have as good reaſon, and better, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their former Oathes of Allegiance and Supremacy to His Majeſty, and of Church-men for their obedience to the Biſhops: you put all into a confuſion.</p>
               <p>You ſay <hi>deſtruction here, and damnation hereafter, is a hard ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but you will make it out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would fain know how: you ſhall never make it out by your example of the Gibeonires, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.15. you are very much taken with that pattern, you repeat ſo frequently <hi>what a lye they told to children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>how crafty and wily they were to obtain their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, how they cheated</hi> Joſhua <hi>and all the Princes.</hi> I am perſwaded you laugh in your ſleeves, to think you have done ſo too with the whole Nation; but I cannot finde that this makes any thing for that you would conclude from it, becauſe your Covenant was made and impoſed, as I told you before, without <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Princes conſent. It's true, the Gibeonites to ſave their lives, did this in fear; but your Covenant was made in ſubtilty to uſurp authority over others, &amp; to deſtroy a legal, ancient Church-Government, and to take away the lives of all that ſhould reſiſt you, under pretence of a Vow made to Almighty God, which you ſay you are bound to perform. Now if you are pleaſed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſcope of the Text you alledge, although the Gibeonites came with their old ſhooes and ragged garments (as your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſome ſay, did at firſt to gain their ends) [when you hired them] yet there it ſeems to intimate a ſecret permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of God, that <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the Princes ſhould be deluded by them, becauſe they did not firſt ask counſel from him (as men ought to do in all that they go about) whoſe command was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them all: (I am certain you had no ſuch command to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us.) But God did ſo highly favor his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that he would have them all free men, and none of them to be employed in any ſervile work; wherefore the Gibeonites were ſuffered by their Covenant to eſcape, that they might be made hewers of wood and drawers of water, for the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> I conſeſs your Covenanters have plaid the wily Foxes as much as ever the Gibeonites did; and by preſſing their example, you ſeem to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their policy and cheat they put upon the Iſraelites. You
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119177:20"/>are yet as free as any men amongſt us, and were ſo before you entred into your Covenant, but I would wiſh you to take heed that you be not the cauſe of your own ſlavery, and receive the ſame reward as the Gibeonites did of their cheating covenant.</p>
               <p>But you ſtill go on, <hi>If God were ſo ſevere for the breach of ſuch a deceitful Covenant between man and man, when they that procured it were ſo baſe and falſe (as the Doctor would make the late Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters) how ſinful and dangerous muſt it needs be for men, upon any pretence whatſoever,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>willfully to break any Covenant with God himſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot acquit you for your fraud in contriving the Covenant, and as to the performing of it, ſince you ſay you made it with God, whoſe counſel I believe you never asked, you ought to have kept it better; for I have ſhewed already that you have falſified your Vow in every Article of it, except in that which was not fawful for you to make or keep, to extirpate the beſt Form in the world of Church-Government. What you ſay farther of <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kah's</hi> breach of covenant with the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> is againſt you; as is alſo the Text you cite, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.2. <hi>I counſel thee to keep the Kings Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God;</hi> for you had the Kings Commandment, and your former Oathes to the King againſt it: ſo then you have more cauſe to repent, and ask God forgiveneſs for the great ſin you have committed, than to go forward in it, adding pe ſeverance to your impiety; which if you do, ſurely God will never ſuffer you to paſs unpuniſhed, neither in this world, nor in the world to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nor will the impoſing, or not the impoſing of it by ſupream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, alter the Caſe; for it is obſervable, that in all ſuch National Vows and Covenants, neither the ſupream Magiſtrates impoſition, or ſo much as conſant, is at all recorded in Scripture, or mentioned; which ſhews there is no neceſſity of either.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely a lye will never choke you, you have eaten ſhame, and drank after it: See <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 35.2. <hi>Jacob makes a Vow, and all that were with him, to put away ſtra ge Gods.</hi> See King <hi>Joſiah's</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.31, 32. <hi>And the King made a Covenant, and cauſed all that were preſent in</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and</hi> Beniamin <hi>to ſtand to it.</hi> Be aſſured that all thoſe inſtances you pick out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119177:21"/>of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the wilderneſs, <hi>Num.</hi> 21.2. or of <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 15. do either tacitely inſinuate, or openly expreſs the conſent of the ſupream Magiſtrate, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was viſibly employed in the firſt Covenant as King, or Supream. I will not cavil about Titles as you do with the Doctor; but there was nothing done of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick concernment without him, although his Command is not alwayes ſet down, for that were needleſs. If <hi>Moſes</hi> was not Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, I pray who was? were they without a Chief Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? He was their General, and what can be done in an Army but by the Generals Commiſſion, ſhall the Soldiers covenant to do what they will without him? As for your ſecond Example of the Covenant made by <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.8, 9. to that I refer the Reader, and as he findes you to deal there, ſo let him truſt you another time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nor can any one inſtance be given throughout the whole Word of God, that any Oath or Covenant, to which the King or Supream Magiſtrate would not, or did not conſent, was upon that reaſon or ground made null and void,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>You are ſtill importunate, and will not be beaten off: I thought enough had been ſaid; your high animoſity and proud ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit proceeds from <hi>Baal-zebub</hi> the god of flies; for let ſlies be driven away never ſo oft, they will return to be nibling. I know you cannot finde it in Scripture, and I think in no Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that Subjects did attempt to make a Covenant, unleſs they went to rebel without the Princes conſent: you are the firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample that ever I read of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is no other but blaſpheming the Gods, to term the late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Bungling Reformers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All is blaſphemy with you that is not for your Covenant, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema, Maranatha;</hi> but the late long Parliament were ſurely no ſuch perfect work-men, to deſtroy one Government that was good, and yet never be able to ſet up any thing but confuſion in the place of it; and therefore I cannot think it any blaſphemy to call your Gods Bungling Reformers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Farliaments indeed may adviſe and conſult with whom they think ſit in matters of Religion and Eccleſiaſtical Affaires, and vote, and paſs them before they offer them to the King; did not they ſo in this?
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119177:21"/>and did not his then Majeſty take them into conſideration, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to ſo much as they gave him time to conſider of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is wiſely ſpoken: They gave him but ſhort time it appears to condeſcend, if he would not do it preſently, they would afford him no longer time to conſider.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But without declaring againſt the reſt, but onely ſuſpending con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent till his conſcience might be better ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And did you ever ſatisfie his conſcience in it? you never ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for that, and had he deolared againſt the reſt, as it is palpable that he did, all that he declared ſtood for nothing in your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Parliaments indeed may, and do well to adviſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, vote and paſs things before they offer them to the King, but what is that unleſs it be conſirmed by his Royal Conſent with <hi>Le Roy veult.</hi> What he did condeſcend to, is lawfully Enacted, but all the reſt is of no force; for it is the Kings Prerogative to conſider of it <hi>Le Roy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adviſera.</hi> What the King oppoſed not, may imply his tacite conſent, but if there were then violence or fear upon him, as at that time, that he muſt do it <hi>velens nolens,</hi> as King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. condeſcended to your Covenant when He was crowned in <hi>Scotland,</hi> I know not how the Laws do interpret Oathes of that nature that are forced: but I believe no Deeds or Obligations made by men in priſon, when they cannot help themſelves, can he pleaded in any Court of Judicature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Proteſtation</hi> May 5. 1641. <hi>which was never offered to His Majeſty at all (being no way contrary or contradictory to the Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance) was never oppoſed or contradicted by him,</hi> &amp;c. Good: you do as much as grant that the Covenants that followed, were both contrary and contradictory, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by him, but you cared not for that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what ails the man to make ſuch a noiſe about the impoſing the Solemn League and Covenant without the then King, who was then abſent?</hi> &amp;c. You allow that he was then King, but he was then abſent. How abſent was he, was he gone out of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious? and who was the cauſe of his abſence? did you not drive him away with your popular Tumults, and all the affronts you could or then durſt put upon him? and what ail you to produce ſuch impertinent proofs of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119177:22"/>they made a Covenant without ſpecial Commiſsion from the Perſian Monarchy.</hi> The Tezt is clear, that they were more obedient to the Heathen Perſian Monarchy, than you have been to King <hi>Charles</hi> a pious Chriſtian King, and ſhall riſe up in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you; for they asked leave, and had their Commiſsions granted from <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> to do what they could for the ſervice of the moſt High God, and to build his Temple; but you took leave without his conſent to diſhonor God, and defile his Temples: had <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> for all their Commiſſions for Gods ſervice, entred into a Covenant to have taken up arms, and to have deſtroyed the idolatrous prieſts in <hi>Babylon,</hi> as you did to deſtroy a Chriſtian well-ordered Church-Government here, and thoſe that were better Chriſtians than your ſelves; you may be aſſured the Perſian Monarchy would never have endured ſuch Rebellion againſt them. Whether his late Majeſty did ever command the renouncing of your Solemn League and Covenant, as you ſay he did not, I cannot tell, or whether there were any Proclamation or Declaration againſt it, yet as I remember there was: but be it ſo, or ſo, it is all a caſe with you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He did publiſh a Proclamation</hi> June 21. 1643. <hi>againſt that other Vow and Covenant, which was about that time taken by the Lords and Commons, and by them appointed to be takeu by every man in the Cities of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and ſuburbs thereof, and through the whole kingdom; the adminiſtring and taking whereof (by ſuch as had not taken it) were by that Proclamation, and the reaſons therein contained, forbidden,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It ſhould ſeem that your Solemn League &amp; Covenant was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by both Kingdoms <hi>Sept.</hi> 11. 1643. but it is very ſtrange that both Kingdoms ſhould take it in one day, you made haſte for fear of the Kings Proclamation to forbid it, but that is moſt for your purpoſe, becauſe there was no Proclamation againſt that, yet they that had taken the former Covenant, were not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Proclamation, becauſe the Proclamation came too late, and they had taken it before it came. I doubt not but the reaſons therein contained were ſufficient to convince them who had taken it before, that they had not done well in taking it without the Kings conſent; and will you tye them that had taken
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119177:22"/>that Covenant which was forbidden by the King afterwards, as well as you do to the Solemn League and Covenant, ſuppoſing they may one contradict the other: but if they were both of the ſame mettal, certainly the Kings Proclamation that forbad the one, did expreſly forbid the other, and argues you to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to a great height of impudence that durſt go on further, being forbidden by him; and you hold thoſe that took the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant after the Proclamation, as much bound to perform it, as thoſe that took it before; for you ſay in many places that the <hi>Kings conſent is neither neceſſary nor requiſite, nor is there any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in Scripture for it,</hi> and to what end then do you make ſuch a ſtir about the reprinting of this Covenant without warrant, (you mean your warrant) <hi>by one who was an enemy to the other So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant,</hi> (to one as well as the other) <hi>as if it had been an interdicting and prohibiting of thoſe that had taken it, to perform it.</hi> To retort your own words upon you, <hi>This is but a meer cheating and gullery of yours, of which it behooves all honeſt men and ſober Chriſtians, to take heed and beware.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nor are Oathes and Covenants once ſolemnly taken, to be caſt off and diſclaimed upon any pretence whatſoever, be there never ſo many defects and failings in the impoſing or making of them, unleſs the matter of them be ſinful, as the Jews was to kill</hi> Paul, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.14.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>you have ſaid enough already,</hi> and too much too I think to little purpoſe; for you run round in a circle until your brains are giddy, and know not what you ſay. Thoſe that took the Covenant before the Kings Proclamation are bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, and thoſe that took it after the Kings Proclamation are bound to perform it, what then do you talk of the Kings Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation? all the queſtion is, if the matter of the Covenant be ſinful, and in ſome clauſes of it you need not queſtion that, for we have proved that already, whatſoever <hi>ſaered</hi> Title you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon it. But your abſurdity for want of the Kings conſent, you would make up by a <hi>Book you ſay you ſince met withal, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance, which have been laid aſide ſo many years.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its true, they have been laid aſide ever ſince the Covenant juſtled them out of doors, but I pray by whom but by thoſe that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119177:23"/>were perverted by your Covenant? Now you would apply the words of that Book to your purpoſe, which as well fit you as a ſowe doth a ſaddle. The words are, <hi>That though there be many infirmities and miſearriages committed in the making and taking of publick Oathes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet no pretence can make ſuch Oathes void,</hi> &amp;c. Thoſe Oathes I ſay were confirmed by King and Parliament, and the matter of them is juſt and equal, which your Covenant wants; and there were ſo many infirmities in the contriving, preſſing, and taking of it, that many wiſe men held it utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to be taken at all, and that thoſe that did take it ſhould repent of their errour, being reſtrained by the Law of God and man from the performance of it. <hi>The reaſons, you ſay, alledged by the Univerſity of</hi> Oxford <hi>in a full Convocation,</hi> June 1. 1647. <hi>why they could not take this Covenant, and another Negative Oath, no way concern the preſent Caſe; for thoſe reaſons tend onely to their own juſtification for their not taking of the Covenant then tendred to them, but not to fall upon others who had already taken it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What irrational evaſions are you forced to? They that took it, are bound to perform it; but the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> had reaſons to juſtifie them why they ſhould not take it: was it not calculated for the Meridian of <hi>Oxford?</hi> if it had been lawful, what reaſons could they have to juſtifie them more than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subjects had? ſo then it ſeems ſome ſimple Proſelytes that you made, becauſe they wanted reaſon to defend themſelves, are hampered in your net, and there they muſt ſtay upon pain of hell fire, and eternal damnation. I have heard of a fool tied by the leg with a pack-thread, who would ſtand, and roar and cry as if he had been bound with iron bonds. You ſtrain at a gnat, and ſwallow a camel; you that were bound with legal Oathes before, as ſtrong as the wit of man could deviſe, and ſnapt them aſunder as if it had been but a twine thread, what do you then prattle ſo much of the ſtrength of your Covenant, which is far better bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken than kept? and if the Covenanters had brought His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to his Crown, they could have been no more importunate for their Covenant than they are; when as it is manifeſt that it was not the Presbyterians that effected this great Work, but it was the apparent hand of God, by making uſe of ſuch Inſtruments as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119177:23"/>he thought good, the Noble, Valiant, &amp; Diſcreet General <hi>Monk,</hi> and the prudent and well-adviſed Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Alleyn,</hi> Sir <hi>Geor. Booth,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Middleton,</hi> Alderman <hi>Robinſon,</hi> and ſome other perſons of note and eminency, who were no ill friends to the Epiſcopal Government, that the Presbytery have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to lay all the claim to what they did, but they muſt needs allow us to have as great an intereſt in them as themſelves; for theſe are perſons of a ſublimer judgement, and are equally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to do juſtice to all, not byaſſed by any factions, or ſurely God would never have proſpered the work in their hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex Jupiter ommibus idem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In your Covenant there was contained renouncing of Popery and Superſtition, Preſervation of His Majeſties Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what Reaſons then could the Scholars of <hi>Oxford</hi> give that they ſhould not take this? If, as the words ſound in common appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of them they are very good, but if they muſt be read backward, or be conſtrued another way, and ſignifie nothing elſe but a trapanning of Subjects to diſobedience againſt their lawful Soveraign, and breaking of his Laws, why ſhould any man that had unadviſedly taken it, be ſo ſtrongly obliged to keep it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In caſting dirt upon that Covenant which His preſent Gracious Majeſty hath ſo highly honored,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>You are reſolved it ſeems, to hold His Majeſty to it; but if it ſhall not ſtand with His Majeſties Honor, you are none of the beſt Subjects to preſs it upon him, taking advantage of his then ſad condition; but we hope that you returning to your due O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, to which you are ſtrongly bound by the Laws of God, and man; and calling to minde your former Loyal Oathes, that you will confeſs that you had no lawful Authority to impoſe ſuch a Covenant upon his Gracious Majeſty, and therefore will of your own accord freely abſolve him from it; or you know (and then it will be no thanks to you) that the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as you grant before) can diſanul and abrogate former Oathes and Contracts, or elſe you will charge ſome with perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which you dare not to name.</p>
               <p>You tell us <hi>that the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland <hi>entred into a Solemn Covenant amongſt themſelves, without their King, before their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119177:24"/>joyning with</hi> England <hi>in this, and the King and Parliament of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>upon a through Debate theneof, declared, though at firſt they reſolved to chaſtiſe them with a puiſſant Army, That our Brethren of</hi> Scotland <hi>had done nothing but what became Loyal and Obedient Subjects,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It is very credible that ſome of your Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> firſt taught you this Covenanting way, and there were too many in <hi>England</hi> confederate with them; and if the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at firſt ſo highly offended, did afterwards to avoid civil Diſſentions, and ſhedding of blood, compoſe the Differences in an amiable way, yet God who ſees the hearts of all men, would not ſuffer ſuch Rebellion to go long unpuniſhed, but chaſtiſed them ſeverely ſoon after, by the hand of <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> who made a full Conqueſt, waſted and ruined what he pleaſed, and brought them into irrecoverable bondage, had it not pleaſed God at length to ſet them free by the moſt happy Return of His Excellent Majeſty <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to His juſt Inheritance; and therefore I hope the Scots will not prove ſo ungratefull to Him, but as good Subjects, being now ſet at liberty by Him, leave off their Covenanting amongſt themſelves without His conſent, and ſubmit to His Royal Government, as their duty bindes them.</p>
               <p>You tell us <hi>of</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James, both of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memories, aſſiſting the Netherlands, (combined not onely without but againſt the unjuſt violence of</hi> Philip <hi>the Second of</hi> Spain, <hi>firſt and chiefly in matters of Religion) and entring into League with them as Free States; which was afterward continued by His late Majeſty,</hi> And why not of bleſſed Memory, as you ſaid of the two former Princes? <hi>in his Expedition for the Relief of</hi> Rochel, <hi>and Alliance with the Prince of</hi> Orange.</p>
               <p>That Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles,</hi> all of bleſſed Memories, did aſſiſt the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> being then poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed States, oppreſſed in their Conſciences by the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> all the world knows ſufficiently, for by this means they are grown from a poor contemptible condition, to be the Potent <hi>Hoogen Mogens,</hi> the High and Mighty Lords of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezland,</hi> &amp;c. which hath coſt the beſt blood of Subjects
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119177:24"/>that <hi>England</hi> had, beſides multitudes of Gentry and Commons that loſt their lives in their defence. The <hi>Netherlands</hi> were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spain</hi> indeed, but they ſtate the Caſe far otherwiſe than it was, or is with us in <hi>England,</hi> how rightly they beſt know. But how far, and upon what grounds of Religion and Policy Princes may afford Relief to Subjects of other Princes that are oppreſſed and enſlaved by them, eſpecially for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake, is too long to diſpute now; certain I am, that the Netherlands were bound in the ſight of God and man, to a great meaſure of thankfulneſs to the Kings and Queen of <hi>England</hi> for their Aſſiſtance, and by conſequence to their Succeſſors and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; but whether they did ſhew it to His late Majeſty during the Wars in <hi>England,</hi> or to His Royal Iſſue in their exile amongſt them, and to ſuch poor ſubjects as followed them, I know is a queſtion eaſily to be reſolved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus I have given you ſome Pattern of Covenanting Chriſtians, beſides the holy League in</hi> France.</p>
               <p>Why Sir, what Patterns are they? when you ſpeak of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, you mention no Covenant they took, but ſay they combined together; but your Patterns are, you ſay, <hi>the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament in</hi> England, <hi>and your Brethren in</hi> Scotland.</p>
               <p>Surely the man is beſides himſelf: The Doctor complains of your Scotch Covenant, and that which was ſet forth by the two Houſes of Parliament without the Kings conſent; and he ſaith further, that there were never any ſuch Covenanting Chriſtians heard of untill the Papiſts covenanted together to deſtroy the French Proteſtants; and if you have any other Patterns to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, he challengeth you to do it. In anſwer whereto you ſay <hi>idem per idem:</hi> your Patterns are <hi>the two Houſes of Parliament, and our Brethren of</hi> Scotland: the Boys in the ſtreets will hiſs at you.</p>
               <p>You adde, <hi>that you forbear to mention</hi> Germany, <hi>the</hi> Cantons <hi>the</hi> Albigenſes, <hi>and others, becauſe you had ſaid enough already,</hi> when as you had ſaid juſt nothing; and what you now ſay is as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous as the former. <hi>You will not mention</hi> Germany, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when as you do onely mention it and no more; but for any Covenants they entred into without their Princes conſent, if you knew of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119177:25"/>any you ſhould have mentioned that, or elſe hold your peace, but it is clear you could finde none, which is ſufficient to ſhew your falſhood and folly, and blaſphemy in the cloſe, who dare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your Covenant with our ſacred Covenant made with God in Baptiſm, wherein we are ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt, and ſpiritually waſhed from the guilt of original ſin.</p>
               <p>Give me leave to make a ſhort digreſſion, if it be any, to ſhew how hurtful it is to binde the King and his Subjects to ſtand to the Covenant: We honor our Kings here, as Chriſts Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents upon earth, and although they are compaſſed with human infirmities, and are reſtrained by good Laws from doing wrong, becauſe of the largeneſs of their power, yet they ought not to be bound with Saint <hi>Peters</hi> bonds, or hindred from doing any good they can. You know that God hath given to the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a miraculous Gift of Healing moſt ſcroffulous Tumors, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Kings Evil,</hi> (for every good gift comes from God) and that many hundreds have been healed by His Majeſties touching of them ſince His happy Return, who could finde no remedy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from Chyrurgions or Phyſicians, and divers periſhed for want of help; and if the Chriſtian Kings of <hi>France</hi> can do the like, it is but a farther Confirmation of the certainty and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of it: now when they perform theſe Cures, ſome wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Biſhop or Epiſcopal Divine waiteth on them, repeating the Promiſe of our bleſſed Saviour to his Church (over which the King is held by us to be Supream in his Dominions) <hi>They ſhall lay their hand upon the ſick, and they ſhall recover,</hi> Mark 16.18. If your Covenant will not allow this to be done by them, but that poor people muſt periſh for want of Cure, when God hath ſo graciouſly provided it for them, how do you think it poſsible the people will endure ſuch a Covenant?</p>
               <p>I have been told that ſome ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> ſhould ſpeak evil of it, who would ſpeak no better of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Napkins, or of the ſhadow of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> paſsing by. I do not finde that this way of healing was practiſed here, at leaſt ſo frequently, before <hi>Edward the Confeſſor</hi>'s dayes, who is well repreſented on the Royal Exchange, under a double capacity of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Prieſt,</hi> with a Crown on his head, and a Bible in his hand; and from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119177:25"/>him it deſcended to his Succeſſors; yet if I forget not, I have read ſomething of King <hi>Lucius</hi> to this purpoſe, who was the firſt Chriſtian King here, when <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> lived in this Iſland. But ſhould any man ask a reaſon why the King doth not cure all Diſeaſes as well as that, or why it was not practiſed ſo often at leaſt, in former days? it would be to, tedious to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Sympathies and Antipathies, of <hi>Thora</hi> and <hi>Antithora,</hi> or of ſuch providential wayes wherewith our good God doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſupply mankinde with helps againſt all defects and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences where we ſtand in need: One may as well forbid the uſe of the Mariners Compaſs, as if it were performed by ſorcery or inchantments, becauſe we cannot give a certain reaſon why the Loadſtone ſhould attract iron as it doth; or the Needle ſhould point alwayes to the North. I ſhall onely aſsign two reaſons of His Majeſties curing the Evil. The firſt ſhall be, that it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that this Evil is more frequent, and increaſeth more now than it did of old, by reaſon of change of Diet, or from what cauſe ſoever it may proceed wherein we differ from the Ancients, and therefore God hath furniſht us with this remedy againſt it. And ſecondly Chriſtianity waxing cold, and men being more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joct to rebel againſt the Supream Magiſtrate than of elder times; for ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writes to <hi>Timothy, That in the laſt dayes pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous times ſhould come, that men ſhould be Traytors, heady, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.4. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 Pet. 3 3. <hi>There ſhall come in the laſt dayes ſcoffers, walking after the rown luſts, ſuch as deſpiſe Government,</hi> chap. 2.8. <hi>preſumptuous, not being afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities, and therefore</hi> 1 Pet chap. 2.13. <hi>he commands all, Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man, to the King as Supream: and</hi> verſe 17. <hi>Fear God, honour the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that Subjects might live more peaceably in obedience to the King, this may be none of the leaſt occaſions, God having hereby diſcovered unto us, that he hath beſtowed upon the King this divine Vertue of Healing ſome of the moſt general and ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Diſeaſes amongſt the people, more than he hath given to any other men.</p>
               <p>I would we knew the extent of your Covenant, if we muſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119177:26"/>obey it, I do not ſee but moſt degrees of Honor, the Nobles as well as of the Clergy, muſt be levelled by it. It may be the Order of the Garter will be allowed for no better than an old Popiſh Ceremony, fit to be aboliſhed, if you may <hi>tanquam ex cathreda,</hi> interpret the ſenſe of your Covenant, which you hold to be as infallible as <hi>Rome</hi> doth her Church, all muſt believe it under pain of damnation, call but your Covenanters the Church, and I find no difference. But to return to Epiſcopacy, methinks it is high time Biſhops ſhould be reſtored with more power than formerly, which will be but moderate Epiſcopacy, in regard of the great increaſe of Schiſms and Hereſies, and the dangerous times we are fallen into.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But whom do you call your dear Mother of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? <hi>Pray what is ſhe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here according to your ſcurrilous way of jeering, you proceed to ſpeak non-ſenſe, it ſeems you are but an ungracious, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſon, your Mother is grown poor by many of your plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſequeſtrings, and now you will not know her. Doth not St. <hi>Paul</hi> call himſelf the Father of thoſe Churches he had begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Chriſt? and why then cannot the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually and metaphorically be called our Mother, whoſe breaſts we ſuck in the two Sacraments of Baptiſm, and the Holy Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>That Kings ſhall be the Churches Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Fathers, and Queens Nurſing Mothers:</hi> Are you ſuch a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and underſtand not that, or will you quarrel with the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for it?</p>
               <p>As for your Poſt-ſcript of Doctor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers</hi> Model of Reformed Epiſcopacy, the Learned Doctor <hi>Bernard</hi> being now living, is able to give the beſt account of that; but I hope I have given you a good account of all the reſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:119177:26"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THe Reader may, if he pleaſe for his own better ſatisfaction, compare the Arguments of <hi>Anonymus</hi> with thoſe of Mr. <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary Crofton,</hi> who is reported to be the <hi>Goliath</hi> of the Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>London,</hi> and he ſhall finde them to be birds of a feather, having little more to ſay for themſelves. <hi>Qui utrumvis recte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit, ambos, immo omnes noverit:</hi> anſwer one, and anſwer them all. I would counſel them, if they will take my advice, to live peaceably, and not to diſturb the Church of God, whereof they are members, conſidering how dangerous Schiſms are to let in Popery, Judaiſm, Turkiſm, Paganiſm, and all manner of impiety, to the ſubverſion, if it were poſſible, of the Chriſtian Faith, we are all as brethren travelling to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan:</hi> Let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that Charge <hi>Joſeph</hi> gave to his brethren going to their earthly <hi>Canaan, See that you fall not out by the way.</hi> God grant us all a right underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>There are others ſince <hi>Zach Crofton,</hi> that plead for a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our Church in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, let them by ſtrength of Argument prove the neceſſity the pretend, and let us have the ſame liberty in an amiable way to defend it, and I doubt not of a good iſſue; always with this proviſo, That the Covenanters ſhall not when they are at a loſs, run back to ſhelter themſelves under their Covenant, as they uſe to do. We know what <hi>Ajax</hi> ſaid of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes, Et quaerre cenſciui Arma:</hi> they need not blaze it about ſo much, to perſwade the people things are ſo extream bad in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> their beſt way will be, if they mean peaceably, to make their Addreſſes to the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhops, and by their advice, if there be any thing that will not agree with theſe mens queezy ſtomachs, ſomething may be more fully explained to give them ſatisfaction, which I believe for my part is impoſſible for any men to do, they are ſo inconſtant in their judgements and reſolutions; and that it would not pleaſe them long, if they were ſuffered to make the Alteration them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: they will ſtand to nothing unleſs their <hi>Dalilah,</hi> the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, may be allowed to be Supream Governor; and that is the
<pb facs="tcp:119177:27"/>main reaſon of the great noiſe they make for want of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which if there were ſuch neceſſity for it as they would make the world believe there is, nothing hinders more than their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant: for to what end ſhould the wiſeſt men upon the earth alledge Scripture, Councels, Fathers, to confirm any Truth, if when all is done, it will not ſquare with their Lesbian Rule, their leaden Covenant which will bend every way, and which alone they will admit to be the meaſure of it, it ſhall be held by them for no Reformation at all. Wherefore all that are diſ-ſatisfied with our Church in Doctrine or Diſcipline, muſt renounce the Covenant, if they expect any thing to be amended, and, which is the readieſt way to ſet things to rights, reſt in the wiſe and pious determination of our Anceſtors, who ſetled Epiſcopal Government here, the livelyeſt pattern this day in all the world, whereby all erronious and heterodox Opinions may be kept down, and Religion ſetled and continued according to the true Rule, which is the word of God.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Coronis</hi> ſhall be an Hexaſtick of Sir <hi>John Sucklings,</hi> never to be forgotten:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>IF I were of your Covenant,</l>
               <l>Then you would call me <hi>John of Gant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or one of high renown:</l>
               <l>But now I am <hi>John for the King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You will call me a poor <hi>Suckling,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſo you'l cry me down.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
